<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rival mother a late true history: digested into a novel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57352</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831141</idno>
  <idno type="VID">35603</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240891402</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831141</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831141e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2039:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rival mother a late true history: digested into a novel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 123, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Baldwin, near the Oxford-Arms-Inn in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35603:1"/>
            <p>THE RIVAL MOTHER; A LATE True History: Digested into a NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms-Inn</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:35603:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35603:2"/>
            <head>THE RIVAL-MOTHER.</head>
            <p>IN one of the most Delightful places of <hi>France,</hi> two Ladies, no less Eminent for the greatness of their Beauty, than that of their Quality, taking their walk along the Canals, which encompass'd a spacious Park, the Youngest of them broke the Silence, which they had observ'd from the beginning of their Divertisement, by addressing her self to another of them, in these words:</p>
            <p>
               <q>How comes it, my dear <hi>Asteria,</hi> that you still continue to be Injurious to the Friendship there is between us, in not acknowledging to me, what your long Retirement in the Country, and your Melancholy do but too much assure me of? And are you resolv'd, never to recall, and reassume, that unconcern'd and divertive Humour, which was so high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35603:3"/> Contributary to the Joy and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faicton of your Friends? You are yet too Young, and too Beautiful to make so early a Renunciation of the World, wherein the Nobleness of your Extraction and your high Merit have plac'd you in so consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable a Rank. And though the Death of <hi>Ortemon,</hi> on whom you were bestowed e're you were well fit for the Management of Man, may haply give you some occasion of Grief, yet methinks you might derive some Comfort hence, that it is now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Three Years since you lost him. But since I had observ'd, before that Loss happen'd to you, that you were subject to the same Sadness, which I perceive you cannot even now over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; am I not to imagine, that it is the Effect of some Passion, it being not within the reach of my Abilities, to find any other Cause of it?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>You afford me matter of much Astonishment, my dear <hi>Emerida,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Asteria,</hi> that it should be so long e're you could find, that I had good reason to break off my Acquaintance with the World. I have seen and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35603:3"/> known enough of it, to raise in me a disgust of its Enjoyments, and a desire to pass away my time amidst the Charms of Solitude; which since you affect as much as I do, and would make as frequent recesses from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, if your Domestick Affairs would permit, how can you desire to see me involv'd in new Dangers, out of which I fear it would not be so easie for me to extricate my self, as I have done out of those wherein I have already been concern'd, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my self to be subject to a sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of whatever makes any pretence to Merit?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Ah! My dear <hi>Asteria,</hi> reply'd <hi>Emerida,</hi> how gladly would I leave you in that happy State, could I but believe that you were in it; but you will Pardon me, if I doubt it. I am willing to acknowledge, that when a Person enters into Solitude, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Passion, he may continue in it with greater Tranquility and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than in the greatest Citi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s: but if such a one carries some weakness along with him, we find his Indispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition augmented, by the time he has
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35603:4"/> there, to reflect upon it, and to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour it by those pleasing Idea's, which smite the Imagination so much the more dangerously, the more they represent the delightful Objects, the loss whereof do occasion a regret.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria</hi> having continu'd a while in suspence, as reflecting on the precedent Discourse, broke it up with a deep Sigh, and then embracing <hi>Emerida,</hi> she said to her, <q>Though there be not any thing I would keep secret from you, yet take it not amiss, if I tell you, that if my Soul were chargeable with the weakness of being in love, I should be so much asham'd of it, that I would endeavour to conceal it from my self; so far should I be from being willing to acknowledge it to another.</q>
            </p>
            <p>She pronounc'd these last words, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter such a manner, as depriv'd <hi>Emeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> of the freedom of prosecuting a Discourse, about a thing, whereof she was more satisfy'd, than she had been before; and so they continued their walk, till they came to the End of the Park. From which place, having the Prospect of the Road, they saw com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35603:4"/> along, a Chariot, drawn by Six Horses, having one single Person in it. <hi>Asteria,</hi> not knowing who he was, took <hi>Emerida</hi> with her, and they hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves behind a Palizado; by which the Chariot passing, <hi>Emerida</hi> look'd through the Boughs, and having discover'd who the Man was; <q>To little purpose, <hi>said she, smiling,</hi> to <hi>Asteria,</hi> do you endeavour to avoid Company; I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion not but the return of <hi>Tazander,</hi> whom I see, will force you to the reception of many Visits from him, if he makes his residence, as long as I am told he will, in these parts.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>All the Visits which shall be made upon the score of Civility, reply'd <hi>Asteria,</hi> are but little trouble to me, because I have the Secret of either shortening, or diverting them; and having hardly ever seen <hi>Tazander,</hi> I do not expect he will be so liberal, as you imagine, of his Visits to me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>While they were thus discoursing, the Chariot overturn'd in the Rivulet, which issu'd, at that place, out of the Canals of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s Park. Those two Beauties were much startled at that Accident, especially <hi>Emerida,</hi> who,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35603:5"/> fearing that <hi>Tazander,</hi> a Person whom she number'd among her Friends, had hurt himself, entreated <hi>Asteria,</hi> to give her leave to proffer him the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of her House; but <hi>Tazander</hi>'s People had so soon refitted what had been broken, that he was gone, e're <hi>Asteria</hi> had resolved what she should do. Whereupon those two amiable Persons got out of the Park into the Road, and, e're they were aware, to the place, where <hi>Tazander</hi> had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd. <hi>Asteria,</hi> who went before, casting her Eye towards the Rivulet, and perceiving a piece of Scarlet Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon fasten'd to the Reeds, she reach'd to it, and found, that at the end of it there was a golden Case, ennamel'd with Blue, and beset all about with Diamonds.</p>
            <p>That Adventure seem'd to her so extraordinary, that she call'd <hi>Emerida,</hi> and having open'd the Case, they found within it the Picture of a very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som Lady: <q>How glad am I, says <hi>Emerida,</hi> to find at last, that <hi>Tazander</hi> is concern'd in Love, after so long a continuance without any Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and whereas he had resolv'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35603:5"/> to regulate his Amours, subservient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his Ambition, I am apt to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that, in this Beauty, he has met with the advantages of Birth and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, as well as the Charms, which this painting Represents. That is to say, reply'd <hi>Asteria,</hi> that he is so well conceited of himself, as to Court a Person, of whom he is not so worthy, as he imagines. When you shall be better acquainted with him, says <hi>Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida,</hi> you will judge more favourably of him. He is well enough stock'd, as to Wit and Worth (not to say any thing of his Extraction and Estate, whereto you are no Stranger) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the advantages, which he ought to have found, in the Person whose Picture we see. Then admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Painting: What an excellent Symmetry is there in this Face, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued she! How rarely well is this Mouth drawn! and what discoveries of Ingenuity are there observable in these Eyes! If I had so great a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for <hi>Tazander,</hi> as you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, said <hi>Asteria,</hi> this night should not pass e're I eas'd him out of the trouble he must needs be in. I am not of your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35603:6"/> reply'd <hi>Emerida;</hi> I would have him come and look after his Picture, that he may be oblig'd to tell us the name of this great Beauty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Curiosity of <hi>Emerida</hi> rais'd as much in <hi>Asteria,</hi> and made her wish for a visit from <hi>Tazander,</hi> which upon any other occasion she would have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sraid of. The next day, <hi>Tazander</hi> hearing of their being there, went to visit them. After the first Civilities, they fell into discourse of his Travels, and afterwards came to the precedent days adventure; upon which <hi>Emerida</hi> saying, that it was a happy turn he had not hurt himself: <q>For my part, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted <hi>Asteria</hi> purposely, I do not think him ever the happier Man for it; it is possible he may have lost something upon that occasion, which afflicts him more than a considerable hurt would have done, especially if it were such a thing, as his Mistress's Picture, or some other present, which he had received from her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I cannot have made any such loss, says <hi>Tazander,</hi> as having never obtain'd any such favour, nor indeed ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sir'd it. Had I ever receiv'd a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35603:6"/> it should have been so well set up, as not to be easily lost. You are much deficient in point of sincerity, reply'd <hi>Emerida;</hi> and the amiable Person, who has presented you with hers, is much to be bemoan'd; and it must be inferr'd, that you seldom see it, when you can be a whole day, without perceiving that you have lost it. I apprehend not what you say, replies <hi>Tazander;</hi> at least, if I have lost any thing of that importance, I have not yet found that I have done so.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The two Ladies lookt upon each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not knowing what to think of that answer, and whether they should not imagine that some other person, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides <hi>Tazander,</hi> had lately pass'd by that place, where they had found that Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and so that they ought not to attribute that loss to him. In fine, <hi>Emerida</hi> desirous to be fully satisfied, resum'd the Discourse, and said to him: <q>If I am to believe answerably to what I have seen, I cannot doubt of your being in Love; and if I give any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what you say, I still find you the same insensible Person: but, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35603:7"/> deliver me out of this perplexity, see said she, whether you know this love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Picture.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> having fix'd his Eyes a while on what they shew'd him: <q>Now, Ladies, said he, smiling to them, do I not repine at the disadvantagious Judgments which you pass upon me. I must acknowledge, that yesterday I lost this Picture; and there cannot be a greater argument of its not repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting any Person that I am in love withal, than that it has been so long e'er I perceiv'd that I had lost it. What you say, replies <hi>Emerida,</hi> seems very strange; for it is not ordinary, that a Person of your Quality should carry about him any other Picture, than that of his Mistress. If I were the object of your Love, interrupted <hi>Asteria,</hi> I should never forgive you these two great Crimes, that of losing my Picture, and that afterwards, of denying that you lov'd me. I am afraid, Madam, reply'd <hi>Tazander,</hi> that, to take of the ill Opinion you have of me, I shall be forc'd to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to you the Secret of a very inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Friend. I find you extreamly at
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35603:7"/> a loss, what to do, replies <hi>Emerida,</hi> and I know not which of the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities you will endeavour to avoid; to wit, that of leaving us to censure you so disadvantagiously, as we do, or that of revealing the Secret, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have been entrusted. Had it been committed to my trust more seriously, reply'd <hi>Tazander,</hi> I should really be at the loss you speak of; for though it be one of the greatest wishes I have to make in this world, that I may have a fair Character in your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, yet I should think my self ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd not to tell you, what I had been intreated never to discover. But, to my good Fortune, I can as well satisfy your Curiosity, as keep my self in good repute with you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He deliver'd these last words with a submissive smile, and then assuming a more serious look, he went on thus, <q>There is not any necessity, Ladies, that I should give you an account what kind of person <hi>Eurimantes</hi> is; his Extraction, his great Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his Merit cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to you, he being one so eminent in the Province where we now are;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35603:8"/> nay, possibly, you may have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, that there hath always been a great intimacy between him and my self; yet so it happened, that notwithstanding the Friendship he pretended to have for me, I must confess, that for the space of Four Years; that is, from the time he hastily left his own Habitation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any one's knowing the cause of it, he was not pleas'd to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it, even to me, during all the Progress and Travels wherein we had been all that while jointly concern'd. This I took somewhat unkindly at his Hands, yet made not the least discovery of it to him; save only, that when he would have engag'd me in another Voyaging Progress, which would have taken up a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time, I could not forbear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing my unwillingness to go any further, and my weariness of having my Foot every day in the Styrrup. Nay further, considering with my self, that I had no plausible pretence for my absence from home any longer, I us'd what Arguments I could, to induce him to think of his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35603:8"/> Domestick Concerns; but not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with him, it happened, that, the night before our Separation, foul weather having forc'd us to take up our quarters at a small House, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two days Journey of this place, we both lodg'd in the same Chamber: Being got up in the morning, before our Servants were come to wait on us, I found the Key of <hi>Eurimantes</hi>'s little Cabinet in the Lock, and him fast asleep in the Bed. That rais'd in me a sudden Curiosity, insomuch, that I open'd the Cabinet, and, amongst other Papers, I found two Letters, writ in a Womans hand. I read them, and in the former I found these words, without any Subscription.</q>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu will henceforth have but little cause to complain of Fortune; our greatest Persecutor has taken his Progress out of this world, and the others are already come of our side, by a change, which Heaven it self has been pleas'd to make, in order to the rewarding of your Constancy. I hope, within few days, to assure you, that you may have access to me, without fearing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35603:9"/> that any thing shall again separate us. In the mean time I send you, what you have so often desir'd of me, my Picture, which when you look upon, I hope you will pass away, without melancholly, the remainder of an absence, which is as cruel and afflictive to me, as it is to your self, how well soever I may be assur'd, that it will soon be at an end.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <q>I should have had some reason, upon this discovery, to have been dis-satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd at the little Confidence, which <hi>Eurimantes</hi> had in my Friendship, if, upon a Self-Examination, I had not found my self capable of being as careful in concealing a Secret of that importance. However, I would search a little further, and see whether I could find out what Lady it was, who treated my Friend with so much Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Familiarity; and so having felt in the Cabinet, I found the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, which you have return'd me. As I was going to open it, our Servants came in, and <hi>Eurimantes</hi> awak'd, which made me hastily Lock up the Cabinet, not having the leisure to put the Letters and Picture into it.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35603:9"/> But not being able, when I had the time to examine it, to find out who she was, I several times press'd <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes,</hi> before I left him, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to me that he was in Love. Which he obstinately refusing to do, I was once in a mind to convince him of it; but, upon other thoughts, I resolv'd to punish him, in not resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to him the Picture and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, till he were return'd home, which will be, as he assur'd me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two or three Months.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>How am I troubled, says <hi>Emerida,</hi> that we cannot make any discovery of the Lady, who is so favourable to <hi>Eurimantes.</hi> I had fancy'd it a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to my self, that this Picture might belong to you, and that you should no longer continue in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of a Passion, which Men must be sensible of, at least once in their lives.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Tazander</hi> was going to make some answer to <hi>Emerida,</hi> word was brought to <hi>Asteria,</hi> that two Ladies, near Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of hers, were come to give her a visit; which for the present inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Conversation. When those
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35603:10"/> Ladies, and the Men, who came along with them, had made their Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to <hi>Asteria</hi> and <hi>Emerida,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd their gladness at the return of <hi>Tazander,</hi> after his so long Travels, they fell into discourse about several indifferent things, and having made but a short visit, they went away, and took along with them <hi>Tazander,</hi> whose House was not far from theirs.</p>
            <p>As soon as <hi>Asteria</hi> found her self dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingag'd, she went out to take a walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the Park, where having staid a considerable time, <hi>Emerida</hi> thought fit to go and look for her, and found her fitting in a Green Arbour. She came so suddenly upon her, that she could perceive <hi>Asteria</hi> wiping her Eyes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a plentiful shower of Tears. 'Have you not yet says <hi>Emerida</hi> to her, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently tormented me, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment of what afflicts you? <q>You have but lately been inform'd, that, how precautious soever a Person may be in disguising and palliating his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, fortune does many times make it her divertisement to discover them; and that <hi>Eurimantes</hi> should have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd <hi>Tazander,</hi> by a sincere acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35603:10"/> of his advantages, since that Confidence would have ingag'd him to keep his Secret. It matters not, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Asteria,</hi> he will not have any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to make to himself, of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving betray'd his Mistress. Though the keeping of a Secret were necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in reference to Men, reply'd <hi>Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida,</hi> the case is not the same, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to us. Cannot we, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny injury or offence to those who love us, express the advantagious Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we have for them, since it makes for their Reputation? But, said <hi>Asteria,</hi> sighing, when we are sensible of our weakness, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to overcome it, is it not more rational to conceal it, and to spare our selves the Shame, which must accrue to us, from an acknowledgment so hard to be made?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria</hi> spoke these words with so mournful a tone, and had so small a command of her Tears, that <hi>Emerida</hi> closely imbracing her, made her this reply: <hi>Ah, my dear</hi> Asteria, <hi>I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been but too Jocose in all I have said to you; but now I perceive there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of being more serious, since you
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35603:11"/> have made me an over-manifest discovery of some great trouble which lies upon you, and therefore I cannot forbear begging your acknowledgment of it to me, and your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of this firm persuasion; that, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you as I do, with the greatest tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness imaginable, if I am so unfortunate, as not to alleviate, I will bear some part of your affliction. The more easily to induce you, not to conceal any thing from me, I dare tell you plainly, that it is in a manner out of all question, you are highly concern'd in the ingagement of</hi> Eurimantes. <hi>Ah cruel</hi> Emerida! <hi>says</hi> Asteria <hi>to her, why do you ingage me to acknowledge Sentiments, which, though they have ever been innocent, and, to the Person who occasion'd them, unknown, yet have caus'd me so much Shame and Grief to this very day? But what you already know of them, together with the esteem I have for your Friendship, and the confidence I have of your discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, force me, my dear</hi> Emerida, <hi>to this violence, in order to your satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon having wip'd her Eyes, she resum'd the Discourse, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thus. <hi>You do well remember,</hi> Emerida, <hi>that the great Friendship and Intimacy there was between</hi> Eurimantes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35603:11"/>
               <hi>and</hi> Artemon, <hi>gave the former a fair pretence of making frequent visits at our House. My small stock of experience, and his reservedness and wary deportment ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving hindred my perception of the Love he had for me, I innocently favour'd him so far, as to make it appear to him, that his advantages gave me satisfaction, and that I could not forbear grieving at any thing that troubled him. But it happen'd one time above all the rest, that being alone with me, he continu'd a good while in a kind of extasie, or dreaming unmindfulness of the Circumstances he was in. Which I much wondering at, ask'd him so often what the reason of it might be, that at last my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence was punish'd, and I have this eternally to reproach my self withall, that I gave him the boldness to make a confident acknowledgment of his being in Love with me, before ever I was</hi> Artemon<hi>'s: That he was upon the taking of some desperate Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, when, upon his return after a small Journey he had taken, he understood that I was another Mans: That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all his endeavours, to smother the Affection he had for the Wife of the best of his Friends, he could not overcome his Passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that if I had not guess'd at it,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35603:12"/> he would have kept it secret all the remain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Twas then, my dear</hi> Emerida, <hi>'tw<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> then, continu'd</hi> Asteria, <hi>that you shoul<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have seen me, or rather you should ha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> known all the Transactions of my Soul, i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> order to an estimate of my Indignation a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst</hi> Eurimantes, <hi>and against my self I could not find any expression picquant e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nough, to make him apprehend the enormit<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of the Crime he had committed against me▪ and I thought it not a sufficient punishmen<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to me, that, with the greatest resentmen<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> imaginable, I reproach'd my self with m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> extream Imprudence. In short, after<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> had, by words, without any Order or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection, eas'd my self to him of some part of my Resentment, I would not be appeas'd, notwithstanding all the assurances he gave me of his Penitence, and of his never speaking to me any more of his Passion. I told him he had too highly offended me, in that he had presum'd to tell me, that he lov'd me, and that since I ought not to pardon him such an act of confidence, even though I were uningag'd, he might well judge, that in the condition I then was, I should be less apt to do it. In fine, that very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, of his thinking me weak enough,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35603:12"/> not to disapprove of his Love, wrought so cruel an effect upon my Apprehensions, that I disdainfully left him, with this resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That I would henceforth look on him as a mortal Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet did not this rigorous treatment hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from coming to visit</hi> Artemon, <hi>at which I was so highly incens'd, that I sent him word, that if he forbore not those Visits, especially when I was in the House, I would either retire to my Mothers, or haply take some other more strange Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. I would neither look on, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any Letter from him, though impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun'd thereto by a particular Friend of my own Sex, who assur'd me, that his only desire was, to take his last leave of me, and thenceforwards to expiate the fault he had committed by a voluntary banishment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And yet I must acknowledge, that when I was assur'd of his departure, without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leave of, or acquainting any one whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he went, I became sensible, that he was not so indifferent to me, as I had imagin'd; and, notwithstanding all my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and Vertue, I could not forbear fearing that he might take some desperate Resolution. 'Twas then, my dear</hi> Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida, <hi>that you began to take notice of my
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35603:13"/> melancholly, and the disturbances of m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> mind; and if the Sickness, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Death of</hi> Artemon, <hi>at whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> I was really afflicted, had not been a grea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> pretence of my grief, as well as a grea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> occasion of my tears, I should have found i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a hard matter, long to conceal from you▪ what I have now at last acknowledg'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether</hi> Eurimantes <hi>came not so soo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to know my loss of a Husband, or wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> willing to give me the full time, which Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility requir'd, e'er he saw me, he return'd not till a Year after. But though I could not divert his first Civilities, yet I made a shift to avoid the Consequences of them: The tenderness I have ever had for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, suffering me not to mind any thing but the injury he had done me, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected all the Messages he sent, in order to any Pacification; and to give him a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther assurance, that he was not to hope any thing from me, and that I was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to oppose my own inclination, I retir'd hither, upon other pretences, than those which I gave out to the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some days after, having received one of your Letters, which acquainted me, that you were coming to visit me, I went into the great Walk of the Park but was much
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35603:13"/> surpriz'd, to meet</hi> Eurimantes <hi>there. At which, as if I had seen the greatest of my Enemies, I turn'd short, and ask'd why he came to disturb my quiet. I have no such design, Madam,</hi> said he, laying hold of my Garment, and casting himself at my Feet, <hi>and the boldness I take, to appear before you, is only to take my last leave of you. I was in some hope, upon my return, that, since you were at your own disposal, I should induce you to approve of a Passion, which is still the same, in defiance of all your scorn; but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard you condemn it, and that it is not in my Power to smother it, I am going to deprive my self of your sight henceforth, with this Protestation, that no other Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty shall ever move this heart, which has had the confidence to discover to you, what it suffers for your sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I was so incens'd at this discourse, that not knowing whether I should make <hi>Eurimantes</hi> any answer, or get away from him, he was yet speaking when, to my happiness, your Coach appear'd at the entrance of the Walk, which oblig'd him to get into the Wood, and to give me time to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose my Countenance, so that there
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35603:14"/> was no great appearance of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble I was in.</q>
               <q>Yet could I not do i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> so well, but that you perceiv'd some what, which made me tell you that<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was not very well. I have ever sinc<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> pass'd away my time in this pleasan<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Wilderness, without any News fro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Eurimantes;</hi> and here I now find, to my Confusion, that it was an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance in me, to be in a continual fear, lest some misfortune might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to him in his Travels: and to give you a full account of my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, I have flatter'd my self many times, that his Constancy would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me to pardon him. But now that I have so many Arguments of his Fickleness, I should never admit of any Consolation, if he come to know what has pass'd in my Soul, in reference to him, and that it will be less trouble to me to forget him, than it has been to keep his concern undiscovered.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>You give me a great deal of satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, says <hi>Emerida,</hi> to find you in that Sentiment; and indeed his Inconstancy justly deserves your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and the Interest of your Quiet
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35603:14"/> and Reputation, must raise in you, at least, an indifference for a Man, who has made himself unworthy of your Affection.</q> Which discourse she clos'd with all the Reasons and Arguments which she thought fit, to confirm her Friend in so rational a Resolution.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Asteria</hi> made the same Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, yet she had not the command of her heart, as absolutely as she would have had. She sometimes flatter'd her self, that <hi>Eurimantes</hi> lov'd no other than her self, since he could be a whole day e're he perceiv'd that he had lost the Picture; then she fancied that he had receiv'd it from some other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or found it. But after all, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no likelihood it should be as she thought, she would say to her self, <hi>Let us not deceive our selves,</hi> Eurimantes <hi>is unconstant; I ought to forget him, and to be reveng'd on his fickleness.</hi> To fortifie her self in that Resolution, she intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Emerida</hi> to be assistant to her, in the execution of it. But they would have taken pains to little purpose, if, about two days after, <hi>Tazander</hi> had not shewn her a Letter which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from his Friend, wherein he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35603:15"/> press'd the disquiet he was in for the Picture, and importun'd him, by all the Obligations of their Friendship, to send it him back, in case he had found it, affirming that he had seen it in the Cabinet, the day before they parted.</p>
            <p>
               <q>You see, Ladies, <hi>said</hi> Tazander, that <hi>Eurimantes</hi> is in great perplexity; and yet he deserves for his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I should not restore this Picture, till his return, and after he has acquainted me who that beautiful person is, whom it represents.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria,</hi> confirm'd by the Letter of <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> in the Contempt he had for her, was so highly incens'd against him, that fearing then the sight of him, more than she had wish'd it before; <q>Send him back his Picture, <hi>said she, with a greater sally of passion than she could master,</hi> and let him keep to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self a Secret, wherein we do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern our selves.</q>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> being of the same opinion with <hi>Asteria, Tazander</hi> did as they would have him, and writ a Letter to <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> wherein he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd his raillery upon his Love-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, adding, that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pardon him, if he did not acquaint
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35603:15"/> him with the Name of that Beauty, who was so favourable to him, that so he might repair the injury he had done their Friendship, in disguising his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret so long.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eurimantes</hi> made no answer to that Letter, and <hi>Tazander</hi> receiv'd an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that, assoon as he had receiv'd the Picture and the two Letters, he took Post, and was gone no body knew whither. This procedure, which would have vex'd <hi>Asteria</hi> at another time, caus'd her a kind of joy, in that she had a new motive not to love <hi>Euriman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> any longer. From that very day she intreated <hi>Emerida,</hi> never to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to her; and set her mind so far from any thought of him, that, in order to an absolute oblivion of him, she began to divert her self, more than she had done in a long time before; and knowing that the company and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation of <hi>Tazander,</hi> whom she found to be a very ingenious and divertive person, might contribute much to the carrying on of her design, she permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to make more frequent visits than he was wont to do, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their acquaintance.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35603:16"/>
            <p>In those familiar Conversations, whereto <hi>Emerida</hi>'s company did not a little contribute, she was much taken with <hi>Tazander,</hi> who on the other side, finding in her a great Talent of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scernment, and an excellent good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was easily induc'd to discover to her whatever pass'd in his Soul, or related to his Affairs. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment so obliging did insensibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage <hi>Asteria,</hi> to demean her self with the same freedom towards him; and if she had not appear'd to <hi>Tazander</hi> of an Humour extreamly opposite to Love, he might have been inclinable enough to entertain that Passion for her. That misapprehension not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to harbour any Thoughts, but such as were confin'd within the limits of respect, she kept off all the other Sentiments of his Heart at such a distance, that he contented himself with the pure Correspondence of Friendship towards <hi>Asteria.</hi> But such was the misfortune of that fair Lady, that both she her self, and <hi>Emerida</hi> too, who, upon that score, had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten droll'd with the other, were of Opinion, that <hi>Tazander</hi> was really in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35603:16"/> Love with her, and that his tacitur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was a great Argument of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>That perswasion gave her some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet at first, out of a fear of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Tazander</hi> the inconstancy of <hi>Eurimantes.</hi> She thereupon was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to admit of his Love, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling in her self any disposition to answer that Love. But whether her former tenderness had dispos'd her Heart to a second, or that <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> was more capable of being lov'd, then <hi>Eurimantes</hi> had been, it was not long e're she knew that her Heart was not insensible of his Applications. Nay, she sometimes wish'd, that he would presume to acquaint her with his Affection; and yet not being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely prepossess'd with that new Passion, assoon as <hi>Tazander</hi> had said to her, that he had a business of the greatest importance in the World to communicate to her, she was much startled at it, and pretended some pressing Affair, purposely to put off the audience which she must otherwise have given him.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35603:17"/>
            <p>In the mean time, she was attack'd by a diversity of apprehensions; her Modesty made her blush at the very thought of that Declaration, and her Reason made her fear Consequences yet more troublesome than any she had found in the Love of <hi>Eurimantes.</hi> If <hi>Tazander</hi> had not one day met her all alone in her Park, she would not so soon have resolv'd to hear what he had to say to her. And then, not being able any longer to avoid him, she gave the attention he desired, and heard him deliver his Mind to her, to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I find in my self, Madam, so great a deference for your Sentiments, that I am unwilling to conclude any thing upon what is propos'd to me, without first consulting you.</q>
               <hi>Asteria</hi> imagining, by these words, that he intended to speak of some thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uite different from what she was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fraid of, took courage, and at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame time was troubled, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade not his advantage of that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, to make a discovery of his Love to her. With these re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, she suffered <hi>Tazander</hi> to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35603:17"/> proceed in his Discourse, in these Terms.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Be pleas'd therefore, Madam, to give me your advice, in the most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Concern of my Life. There is a proposal made for my inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage with a Lady of very great Quality, and a vast Fortune.</q> A Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course so little expected, at a time when <hi>Asteria</hi> might, with so much probability, have thought that she only was possess'd of <hi>Tazander</hi>'s Heart, coming to undeceive her to her shame, her Mind became im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Stage of whatever could be most Afflictive and Cruel, in an emergency so surprizing. And if her Recollection and her Reason had not assisted her to make greater efforts than any she had made in all her Life, to conceal what pass'd in her Soul, she would have discover'd it to <hi>Tazander.</hi> But she would give him no further audience, when he had once told her, that the Name of that fair one, of whom they had spoken to him, was <hi>Eurimonda,</hi> and that she knew her extraction and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. <hi>Asteria,</hi> during this Discourse,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35603:18"/> had the leisure to recover her self out of the disorder she was in, and to tell <hi>Tazander,</hi> that an Affair of that importance requir'd some time to examine it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander,</hi> contenting himself with that Answer, after he had made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Protestation, that he rely'd more upon her, than upon all the rest of his Friends, took his leave of her, leaving her a new Cause of Affliction, when she consider'd, that he who had so great an esteem, had nothing of Love for her, and giving her withal some matter of Astonishment, that she having as great an Estate, and as much Beauty as <hi>Eurimonda,</hi> could yet affect a Man, who was inclin'd to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himself elsewhere, and one, who, for so long time, had had an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for her.</p>
            <p>The thought of the injustice which <hi>Tazander</hi> did her, in causing her so great an Affliction, rais'd in her an Indignation against him, and being disgusted to the highest degree, she se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times said to her self, I must slight him, as he slights me, and there must be nothing left in my Heart, as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35603:18"/> to his Concern, but the pure regret, that I ever had any esteem for him.</p>
            <p>When she had taken this Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, she thought her self so well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd in it, as that she should never change it; and she was extreamly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd, that she had so great a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of her Inclinations: And yet as soon as ever <hi>Tazander</hi> came into her sight, she could not by any means consent, that <hi>Eurimonda</hi> should have him. But afterwards, coming to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that his Applications for that Marriage were not over-earnest, she had this Consolation, that if <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi> had but little Love for her, he seem'd to have much less for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>This reflection having wrought some tranquility in her mind, she endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to smother the affection she had for him, by avoiding to see him so often. However, she could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear admitting him into an Assignation, which <hi>Emerida,</hi> and some others of her Friends, had appointed at her House, in order to their going all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to visit her Mother, who was come to one of her Houses not far thence.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:35603:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Emanfrida</hi> (so was that Lady call'd) entertain'd them with great joy and Civility. She had in her Company a young Lady, who seem'd to be hardly Fourteen Years of Age. <hi>Tazander,</hi> in a manner dazled at the transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of her Beauty, was desirous to try, whether her Wit were answerable to the Charms of her Features, and so took occasion to give her his hand, as they were going to take a walk in the pleasant Gardens of <hi>Emanfrida,</hi> and soon found, that all was prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in that admirable Person.</p>
            <p>Her resemblance was so great to <hi>Asteria,</hi> that it made him guess she was very nearly related to her; but he was much the more surpriz'd, when, after they were got into an Arbour, he understood that she was her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <q>Nay, Madam, <hi>said he, addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himself to</hi> Emanfrida, say rather that she is her Sister.</q> Whereupon <hi>Asteria,</hi> assuming the Discourse, said to him, by a Sentiment which made her blush, <q>I do not think, that it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the score of my Beauty, or my Youth, you should so much question my being Mother to <hi>Eliciana</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:35603:19"/> (so was that Young Lady call'd) at least my Friends look upon me, as one that has renounc'd those two ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages. Methinks it is not a thing to be endur'd, <hi>says</hi> Emerida, <hi>smiling,</hi> that for this only Reason, that you had a Daughter at thirteen, and that the Daughter is much about the same Age, you should rank your self a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst those Women who imagine Age coming upon them. I am not inferiour to you, as to Years, and yet I am accounted a Young Woman.</q> These words gave the whole Company occasion to speak advantageously of <hi>Asteria,</hi> and her Daughter, so that they had both of them reason to be well satisfi'd therewith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> had his thoughts so taken up with the Beauty of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> that he did not concern himself much in the Conversation; by which demeanour <hi>Asteria</hi> made a full Discovery, that she was not to hope that he would ever have any Affection for her; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, to shun the occasions of seeing him, and that he might become by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees more and more indifferent to her, she stay'd with her Mother, suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35603:20"/> those who had accompany'd her thither to depart. During her abode there, she us'd all the endeavours ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, to smother the Sentiments of tenderness which she had for <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Whenever she thought her self Mistress of them, the satisfaction and serenity of her mind were visible in her Countenance, and when she found them reviving, and gaining ground upon her, she fell into an extream pensiveness and disquiet of mind.</p>
            <p>During this distraction of thoughts, over which she would have the Victory, whatever it cost her, she took the strangest Resolution that haply ever was heard of: And for the better suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of it, she sent to entreat <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merida</hi> to come to her, and craftily to engage <hi>Tazander</hi> to accompany her. <hi>Emerida</hi> acquitted her self of the charge impos'd upon her, and <hi>Tazander</hi> was very glad of that opportunity of visit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and telling <hi>Asteria,</hi> that his Friends press'd him to make a speedy answer, upon the Marriage they propos'd to him, that they might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards enter into Discourses with the Relations of <hi>Eurimonda.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35603:20"/>
            <p>Assoon as he was come to <hi>Emanfri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>'s House, and had the Convenience of Discoursing privately with <hi>Asteria,</hi> he ask'd her, whether she had thought of him. <q>I have, <hi>said she to him,</hi> and I will be so bold as to tell you, that it is more to your advantage, not to make any allyance, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Province where you now are.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I have so great a complyance for your Advertisements, Madam, (<hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd</hi> Tazander) that I am resolv'd to follow them. Nay, I am so far fixt in that Resolution, <hi>continued he,</hi> that I will never engage my self, but with your Approbation.</q> These words put <hi>Asteria</hi> to a change of Colour, and then making an effort to recover her self out of the disturbance she was in, she said to him, <q>As to that point, <hi>Emerida</hi> will give you greater satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, than I can; but I should think my self not much oblig'd, if you did that out of pure complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance, which ought not to be done, but by the Dictate of Reason, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination.</q> She could not forbear closing these words without a sigh,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35603:21"/> though she endeavour'd to divert it; and so left him, out of a fear he might make some Discovery of what she pretended to conceal from him as long as she liv'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> went immediately to look for <hi>Emerida,</hi> who was then gone out to take a Walk, and having not found her, the revery he was in brought him insensibly to a remote and a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate place, where he sate down by a Fountain-side, reflecting on what <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria</hi> had said to him, yet without any hope, or so much as a wish, that <hi>Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida</hi> would speak to him of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> for whom he felt in himself something which might be call'd Love. In the mean time, <hi>Emerida</hi> having been inform'd, that he sought her, came to the place where he was, and began to be smart upon her finding him in so Melancholy a Posture. <q>I was thinking, Madam, <hi>said he,</hi> on what you are to tell me from the Lady <hi>Asteria.</hi>
               </q>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> made answer, that she would satisfie him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day were over. Whereupon she chang'd the Discourse, examining in her Thoughts, how she should make a Discovery to him of the Person
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35603:21"/> whom <hi>Asteria</hi> desir'd that he would prefer before <hi>Eurimonda.</hi> Some time after, <hi>Asteria</hi> and <hi>Eliciana</hi> casually passing into another Walk, not far from them, yet so as that they did not perceive them, <hi>Tazander</hi> being still full of the same thought, said to <hi>Emerida,</hi>
               <q>See, Madam, there go two transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Persons, who cannot be too much admir'd.</q>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> thinking that occasion favourable to her design, made him this answer, smiling, <q>What, your meaning seems to be, that you are so highly pleas'd with both, that I conceive, you would be much at a loss which to take, if you had your choice of them. I am so far unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of <hi>Asteria,</hi> reply'd <hi>Tazander,</hi> that I never durst transgress the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of that profound Veneration which I owe her. If your Respects be so great for the Mother, says <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merida,</hi> can you not find in your Heart to have some tenderness for the Daughter? I am unwilling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Tazander,</hi> to make you acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all that I feel for her sake, since I should express Sentiments, which it were requisite that I should
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35603:22"/> smother, or such as I should see con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, assoon as I should make a Discovery of them. You are defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, in point of confidence, reply'd <hi>Emerida,</hi> and that you may assume as much as you stand in need of, I am to tell you, that you may pretend to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and never fear that <hi>Asteria</hi> will propose any other to you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The happiness you put me in hopes of is so great, Madam, <hi>said</hi> Tazander, <hi>over-joy'd at what had been said to him,</hi> that, if I were not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sur'd of your being one of my best Friends, I could not credit your words: However, you will give me leave, not to be absolutely convinc'd of it, till such time as I shall have receiv'd the assurance thereof from her own Mouth, who has the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal of a Heart, which I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my self uncapable and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to gain.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He thereupon left <hi>Emerida,</hi> and went to look for <hi>Asteria,</hi> taking the same way, which she and <hi>Eliciana</hi> had gone before: And having understood, that she was retir'd all alone to her Chamber, he made all the haste he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35603:22"/> could thither, and said to her, <q>Can I, Madam, without temerity, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the happiness which <hi>Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida</hi> puts me in hopes of? Or will my submissive Prayers be sufficient, to induce you, to admit of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices which I have vow'd to <hi>Eliciana?</hi>
               </q> These words were utterred with so many Discoveries of Passion, that <hi>Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> easily comprehended, what Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>Tazander</hi> had for her Daughter; whereto she continuing a good while without making any Answer, <q>What, Madam, continued <hi>Tazander,</hi> do you repent you of the kindnesses you were pleas'd to have for me, or am I so unhappy, as to be displeasing to <hi>Eliciana? Asteria,</hi> doing her self a great violence, made him this answer, You injure <hi>Eliciana,</hi> in thinking, that she can have any Sentiments inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stent with that of obeying me, and in doubting, whether she knows not, as well as my self, the advantage it will be to her, if she have the honour to be yours.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander,</hi> transported with joy at those words, cast himself at <hi>Asteria</hi>'s feet, in acknowledgment of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35603:23"/> she did him, while <hi>Asteria</hi> felt a secret grief, not to find him in that posture, as she could have wish'd, in reverence to her self. And so, to close up a Conversation, which gave her some disturbance, she told him, that she was going to acquaint <hi>Emanfrida</hi> with that affair, not questioning but that she would approve of it. She thereupon left <hi>Tazander,</hi> and, desirous to put a speedy Period to a thing which she thought necessary, in order to the suppressing of her Passion, she prevail'd with her Mother, that <hi>Eliciana</hi> should be removed from her, and they both of them acquainted that young Beauty, that she was to look upon <hi>Tazander,</hi> as the Person for whom she was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Eliciana</hi> seem'd to be very much inclin'd to obey her Mother, yet would her Tears have betray'd her, if <hi>Asteria</hi> had not attributed them to the regret it was to her, to part with <hi>Emanfrida,</hi> who had brought her up from her Childhood. So that she had an absolute freedom to sigh, and yet none knew the true Cause of it.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:35603:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxaris,</hi> a young Lord, of a very vast Estate, had had a sight of her at <hi>Emanfrida</hi>'s House, whither he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently came, under pretence of the Friendship and Allyance there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their Families. He had had a Love for her, from her infancy and having first discover'd it by his Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and afterwards by his words, he was so happy as to please her, yet all was so closely carried on, that the Love of <hi>Oxaris;</hi> and Tenderness of <hi>Eliciana</hi> were perceived but by very few Persons. This unhappy fair one, finding her self then design'd for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, could not forbear extreamly grieving thereat; she sigh'd, she wept, she pray'd, that the Heavens would change the Will of <hi>Asteria,</hi> yet all without making any Discovery of the repugnance she had to follow it. But at last the Tenderness of her Age, and the Law she had impos'd on her self to do what in Duty she ought induc'd her to obey, whatever might be the Consequence of it. So that, some few days after, she was not Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented at all, when <hi>Asteria</hi> return'd with her Mother, to the City, where
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35603:24"/> they some time pass'd over the Winter, and took <hi>Eliciana</hi> along with her, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, in a short time, to consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate her Marriage with <hi>Tazander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was discours'd in so many places, and not without some Astonishment, of <hi>Tazander</hi>'s being in Love with <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> after it had been the common report, that he had made his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only to <hi>Asteria,</hi> that <hi>Oxaris</hi> came to hear of it. He at first broke forth into complaints at the fickleness of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and then it came into his Thoughts, that he must either take away the Life of his Rival, or fall by his hands. But the fear of incensing her, whom he could not forbear Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the hope of preventing his Misfortune, made him defer these vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Courses, and to endeavour to find out some expedient, to speak with her privately.</p>
            <p>He found it a hard matter to get that opportunity; but it happening one day, that he met her at <hi>Emerida</hi>'s House, and he thus whisper'd to her, <q>Ought I not to look on all those as Enemies, who have given me the Cruel Tidings, of your being design'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35603:24"/> for <hi>Tazander?</hi> And since you know, that that Misfortune would be insup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable to me, can you your self contribute to the causing of it. Know then, Madam, <hi>continued he,</hi> that the mortal disturbance, which some have rais'd in my Soul, cannot be appeas'd, otherwise than by an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from your self, that you will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver consent to promote my despair, by that change. Be pleas'd to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that Justice, as well as your own kindness, obliges you thereto, since you have not found, in my Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, any thing which might inspire you with Sentiments so inhumane. I know not, <hi>replyed</hi> Eliciana, <hi>sighing,</hi> whether I ought to hearken to you, or not, much less to be perswaded, whether I should do as you say; but this I well know, that I am oblig'd, rather to comply with my duty, than my inclination, that thence proceeded the permission I gave you to Love me, that nothing in the World, though I were to dye of Grief, shall be able to make me oppose the design which <hi>Asteria</hi> has to dispose of me. Ah! Madam, how indifferent have I been to you, <hi>replyed</hi> Oxaris, <hi>wholly trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35603:25"/> with Amazement,</hi> and how dea<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is <hi>Tazander</hi> to you! if we may Cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dit this easy disposition which yo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> have to obey <hi>Asteria.</hi> That argue you know not what Transactions ther<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> are in my Soul, interrupted <hi>Elician<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and that you may the better judge o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> them, I give you my permission, to Act your self, and to make what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest you can, with my Mother; but I must give you this assurance withal, that if you cannot obtain any thing of her, I shall never oppose her Will, but submit to whatever she shall require of me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliciana</hi> perceiving that they were observ'd, and that <hi>Oxaris</hi> was going to make some reply, made up towards the Company, after she had said thus to him; I have made so great a disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to you, of both my weakness and resolution, you never ought to expect any more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxaris</hi> being somewhat comforted, to find in <hi>Eliciana</hi> so much kindness, as to wish that he might be happy, employ'd all the Interest he had with the Friends and Relations of <hi>Asteria,</hi> to gain her Consent, that he might
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35603:25"/> have <hi>Eliciana. Asteria,</hi> who had, as we said before, some particulal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to wish that she might be <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi>'s, excus'd her self upon this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation, that, before <hi>Oxaris</hi> had made any discovery of his Love to her Daughter, she had engag'd her word to another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxaris,</hi> finding he could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail that way, endeavour'd to oblige <hi>Eliciana,</hi> to oppose what was exacted from her by <hi>Asteria.</hi> But <hi>Eliciana,</hi> perceiving that her Mother persisted in her former Resolution, chose ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to expose her self to whatever a Heart is capable of enduring when they would force it to surmount a great Passion, than to disobey her, and imposing on her self a necessity, upon the Consideration of her duty, she would not see <hi>Oxaris</hi> any more, nor receive any of his Letters, though it was impossible for him to forget her, or to have only an indifference for her concern.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxaris</hi> could not have any access to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> but what he got by strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, and artifice, and so he made his advantage of the freedom they take in masquerading, at <hi>Carnival Time,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:35603:26"/> and came disguis'd to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, where the Ball then was, being got near <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> he spoke to her of his Passion, as if it had been to one of his Friends. <hi>Eliciana</hi> made answer, with so much indifference, that, discovering himself to her, he could not forbear speaking to her thus. <q>I must then dye, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, or not Love you any longer; have you consider'd, that if I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the former, you will one day repent you, when too late, that you did oblige me thereto; and are you yet ignorant, that nothing can dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the Passion I have for you? Ah! Madam, <hi>continued he, finding that she made no answer,</hi> what a Cruel thing is it, after I had been the first who had Sacrific'd his Heart to you, after I had been countenanc'd in my Passion, and had resolv'd ever to be the same, what change soever there might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen of your side, what a Cruel thing is it, I say, to find my self cast out, and possibly hated, whilst a Rival insolently Triumphs over my misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</q>
               <hi>Eliciana</hi> being vext that <hi>Oxaris</hi> should entertain her, and make such a Discovery of his Passion, and fearing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35603:26"/> withal that he might be known; <q>You complain, <hi>said she to him,</hi> without any cause; I have ever had a great Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship for you, but give me leave to do my duty, and force me not to wish something worse than your indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. How, Madam, reply'd <hi>Oxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> can you desire what you speak of? As I ought to do it, <hi>replyed she,</hi> so I can do it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>These last words were pronounc'd after such a manner, that they pierced the very Soul of <hi>Oxaris,</hi> who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately thereupon left the Ball in order to his return to his own Habitation, there to resign himself up to Despair: But unfortunately it happen'd, that he met <hi>Tazander</hi>'s Coach, in which there was only one Person, who had a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard on. That unexpected Rencounter giving him a Prospect of all his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, upon a surmise that his Rival was belov'd, and going to be happy, he grew so enrag'd, that, leaping out of his Coach with his Sword drawn, he stopp'd that of his Enemy, and forc'd that Vizarded Person to fight him, by the light of their Torches.</p>
            <p>The Combat ended with a wound,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35603:27"/> which <hi>Oxaris</hi> receiv'd in the left hand, and a pass which he made through the Body of his Adversary, upon which he fell down weltring in his own Blood. Many Persons, who came in too late to separate them, endeavour'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the wounded Person, while <hi>Oxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> having got into his Coach, was conducted to a Friend's, named <hi>Seza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> where being arriv'd, he had hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Patience to suffer himself to be dress'd, e're he writ to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and made <hi>Sezamis</hi> promise him, that, the next Morning, he should carry his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to her, and endeavour to perswade her, that she ought to pardon that just sally of his discontent. He pass'd away the Night between hope and fear, and in the Morning, it was no hard matter for <hi>Sazamis,</hi> as being a Person related to <hi>Asteria,</hi> to see <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> and to deliver <hi>Oxaris</hi>'s Letter, wherein she found these words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Oxaris <hi>to</hi> Eliciana.</head>
                  <p>GReat is my fear, Madam, that when you shall have an account of the Combat, which hath happen'd between <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:35603:27"/> and my self, you will be apt to condemn me. But if you consider, that having so lately found in you such unsuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable marks of your indifference, you will, no doubt, judge, that I could not forbear attacking a Rival, who was coming to receive from you all the kindnesses which you were sometime pleas'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise me, and which I should never endure to be communicated to others. My Life and my Death, depending on the Sentiments you shall have for this Action, I am in expectation, with an inexpressible disquiet, Madam, what Sentence will you pass, either for, or against the unfortunate</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>OXARIS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Assoon as <hi>Eliciana</hi> had read it, <hi>Seza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis</hi> gave her a short account of the Combat, wherein <hi>Oxaris</hi> had been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd; and though he endeavour'd to excuse it upon the impossibility of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding that Misfortune, yet she seem'd to be extreamly incens'd thereat, and look'd upon that Action as a mark of great Contempt, rather than of an excessive Love. From that Sentimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, she pass'd to another, of Compassion
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35603:28"/> for the Misfortune of <hi>Tazander,</hi> and bemoan'd him with such expressions, as would have cast <hi>Oxaris</hi> into despair, if he had heard them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sezamis</hi> much afflicted that he had succeeded so ill in what he had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, was making all the fruitless efforts he could, to appease the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> when they were both infinitely surpriz'd to see <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> coming into the Room, along with <hi>Asteria. Sezamis</hi> knew not what to think of that Adventure, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> k for a piece of enchantment; and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iana,</hi> imagining that <hi>Oxaris</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut a trick upon her, was so highly incens'd against him, that after <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> had saluted her, and was fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Discourse with <hi>Asteria</hi> at one of the Windows, she said to <hi>Sezamis,</hi>
               <q>I know not who has put the greater affront upon me, you, or your Friend, in conspiring together to give me an account of the death of a Person, who, for many Reasons, ought to be henceforth the more dear to me; and to make me believe, that he was mortally wounded by him, whom my duty forbids me to look
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35603:28"/> upon, as I had done at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Ah! <hi>Sezamis</hi> continu'd she, this does infinitely exasperate me, and 'tis such an injury as I shall never forget.</q>
               <hi>Sezamis</hi> Swore, that he was not concern'd in the imposture, related to her what he knew of his Friend; blam'd him, and threatned to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd on him, for having engag'd him to be the Messenger of that false intelligence. With that Resolution, was he disposing himself for his return home, but <hi>Asteria</hi> stopped him, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether he had not bemoan'd <hi>Tazander,</hi> who had been given over for a dead Man all that Nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zamis,</hi> imagining that <hi>Asteria</hi> had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verheard the discourse between him and <hi>Eliciana,</hi> took these words for a piece of Raillery, which made him the more angry with <hi>Oxaris,</hi> when <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> assur'd him, that what <hi>Asteria</hi> said to him was true, and that some Enemy, whom he knew not, having taken <hi>Perintus</hi> (who, being unwilling to be known, had borrow'd his Coach) for him, had mortally wounded him. <q>'Tis possible, says <hi>Asteria,</hi> that he who attack'd <hi>Perintus,</hi> knew him
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35603:29"/> through his Vizard, and never thought of you. I have some ground to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, Madam, <hi>replyed</hi> Tazander, who was yet ignorant that <hi>Oxaris</hi> was his Rival; for I do not think, that I ever injur'd any Man, so as to oblige him to set upon me in the night time.</q>
            </p>
            <p>While he was discoursing upon this adventure with <hi>Asteria, Sezamis</hi> came up close to <hi>Eliciana,</hi>
               <q>Well, Madam, <hi>whisper'd he to her,</hi> you see <hi>Oxaris</hi> is vindicated, and I am no longer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd against him; will not you do the like, and tell me something, which may recover him out of the cruel despair, wherein he is now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd? I know not, <hi>replyed</hi> Eliciana, <hi>with a Countenance which did not argue any thing more of favour towards him,</hi> I know not, whether he had not less displeas'd me, in pretending there had been such a Combat, that so he might penetrate into my Sentiments upon it, than in really designing to kill <hi>Tazander.</hi> Howe're it were, he should have consider'd, that he might have displeas'd me, and it behoves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35603:29"/> me, to let him know, that I ought not to pardon him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sezamis</hi> not being able to appease her, with all the Arguments he could use, took his leave, and brought these unwelcome tidings to his Friend, who having sent him back again, the same day to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and receiving from her no other returns, than those of her continu'd indignation, resolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the Province, partly upon the score of despair, partly upon the Sollicitation of his Friends, who, though there were fair hopes of the recovery of <hi>Perintus,</hi> were yet fearful of the just severity of the Laws. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana</hi> was not so highly incens'd against him, but that it was a sensible Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to her, to think of his absence, out of a reflection, that, in a short time, she should be Sacrific'd to the Passion of <hi>Tazander.</hi> For though she had resolv'd to obey her Mother, yet she thought it so difficult a matter to make <hi>Oxaris</hi> an absolute Exile from her Heart, that she concluded, her Misfortune would be of an equal extent with her Life.</p>
            <p>But she was not so near that Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35603:30"/> as she was afraid. <hi>Asteria,</hi> not being able any longer, without a pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Affliction, to see, that <hi>Tazander</hi> met with, in <hi>Eliciana,</hi> those attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he had not found in her self, began to be more unwilling, than ever, to resign him over to another; and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reas, at first, she would not have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stow'd him on <hi>Eliciana,</hi> but out of a design, to take him away from <hi>Eurimonda,</hi> as soon as she found, that she was going to lose him, she look'd upon her Daughter, as the Person who depriv'd her of that Lover. Her Passion gaining the Supremacy over her Reason, she follow'd the suggestions of it, and endeavour'd, by all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices she could think of, to make a Rupture of that Correspondency of Affections, which she her self had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd between <hi>Tazander</hi> and <hi>Eliciana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon that prospect of her concerns, she would perswade <hi>Tazander,</hi> that <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana</hi> was of a light and fickle humour, and not over-forward to make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments of the kindnesses which were done her. That Artifice having not succeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, she began to commend v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry highly another Daughter, whom
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35603:30"/> she had brought up in a Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us House, from which place she sent for her, out of a design to have her Courted by <hi>Tazander,</hi> thinking it her happiness, to take him away from <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> whom she already look'd upon as her Rival. <q>It was ever my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>said she to</hi> Tazander, <hi>the first time she presented to him her second Daughter,</hi> that <hi>Elamira</hi> would in time be a most beatuiful Person, but now that it is above a year since I have had a sight of her, I find, that, when she shall have attain'd that period of years, and perfection, which her Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster has, she will be the greater Beauty, and with this additional ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that she is of a greater sweetness of Nature, of an humour more grateful and obliging, and of a disposition which is more insinuating, and more capable of pleasing.</q>
            </p>
            <p>These Commendations would not have disgusted <hi>Tazander,</hi> if they had not given <hi>Elamira</hi> the precedency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Sister: Accordingly, that Lover could not be so complyant, as to endure so great an injustice, nor forbear to make her an answer suitably
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35603:31"/> to his own Sentiments. <hi>It must needs, Madam,</hi> said he to her, <hi>argue an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary prejudgment in any one, not to see, that</hi> Eliciana, <hi>in the most negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Mode, will always outshine</hi> Elamira, <hi>though set out with all the advantage of Art and Dressing.</hi> These words were spoken loud enough, to be heard by some Ladies, who were near <hi>Asteria,</hi> and who having confirm'd the opinion of <hi>Tazander,</hi> she thought it no pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to contradict them, and so wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for another opportunity, to take off the Love which <hi>Tazander</hi> had for <hi>Eliciana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I freely pardon you,</hi> said she to him another day, <hi>that being prepossess'd, as you were, you could not perceive the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is between</hi> Eliciana <hi>and</hi> Ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mira; <hi>but I should reproach my self with it, as a great miscarriage, as long as I live, if having that Esteem for you, which I have, I had not in a manner forc'd you to be more happy with</hi> Elamira, <hi>than you could ever be with her Sister, whom I know better than you do; And to assure you,</hi> continu'd she, <hi>that I seek only your Good and Welfare, I promise you far greater advantages with</hi> Elamira,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35603:31"/>
               <hi>than ever you should have had with her Elder Sister. And whereas your Love to</hi> Eliciana <hi>was grounded upon my engaging you thereto, the change of your Affections proceeding also from me, you cannot be reproach'd with Inconstancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander,</hi> who apprehended not upon what Motives <hi>Asteria</hi> was so pressing in this Concern, being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd that she should do so much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and that she should pretend to gain him by Interest, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her in few words, that he was not only uncapable of being mov'd by so disallowable an overture, but also, that he would prefer <hi>Eliciana,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing of Fortune, before the richest Heiress of the Kingdom. <hi>Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> was too perspicacious, not to be convinc'd that she was not to hope any thing by that way. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to gain, by Flattery, the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of a Heart, which her other Artifices had not been able to subdue; <hi>O</hi> Tazander! Cry'd she, after she had continu'd a while in silence, <hi>O generous</hi> Tazander! <hi>How much do I admire your constancy! How few Men are there in the World who have so great a Portion of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35603:32"/> that precious Virtue. And how unjust would Heaven seem to be, if it bestows not on her, whom it has design'd for you, the same Sentiments, and the same know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which I have of your Merit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She thereupon entertain'd him with an elaborate Representation of the happiness, and unhappiness of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, adding, that a Man cannot be happy, if a Woman has not ingenuity enough, to know his Merit, and if she does not esteem it, as she should do; since, without that, <hi>The Love,</hi> said she, <hi>which is at first observable in that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual engagement, is weakned by degrees, dwindles into indifference, and most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly degenerates into aversion.</hi> She en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd him with several other things of the like kind, all which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd, craftily to beget in him an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension, that <hi>Eliciana</hi> was not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of having all those Sentiments.</p>
            <p>Though all these Arguments were not so prevalent, as to convince <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander,</hi> yet the fear of incensing <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria,</hi> by too open an opposition of her, and making her his Enemy, check'd him into a forbearance of contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her any longer. Whereupon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria,</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:35603:32"/> thinking she had shaken him, hop'd, upon another assault, to gain the Post she desir'd. Answerable to that Consideration, she began to have a greater Complaisance for him, than she had yet had, to entertain him more frequently, and for longer time than ordinary, and cunningly to keep both her Daughters from speaking to him, at least where Civility did not dispense with it. Nay, she writ to him several obliging things, under several preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But though her Passion inclin'd her, to make a more open Discovery to him of what she felt for his sake, yet her disdainful humour, and her Virtue diverted her from following its advice. And so not finding <hi>Tazander</hi> dispos'd to Love her, as she had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd her self, she was so highly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted thereat, that she continually made secret reproaches of it to her self, and charg'd her own Heart with weakness and Cowardise. In fine, ready to burst with regret and shame, she could hardly endure her self; and considering, with a certain indignation, him who was the cause of her distracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet had not the same Sentiments
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35603:33"/> for her, which she had for him, she began to look on him, as the Enemy of her quiet and happiness, and so came gradually to hate him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, being equally possess'd by those two most enrag'd Passions, she deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd, never to consent to <hi>Tazander</hi>'s Marriage with <hi>Eliciana,</hi> but to defer it from time to time, upon divers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</p>
            <p>According to these Measures she manag'd her Affairs, and indeed it happen'd, at that time, that she had a very plausible pretence, by the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of <hi>Emanfrida,</hi> whom, before her Death, she perswaded, to settle all her Estate immediately upon her self, having previously represented it to her, that it was the surest expedient, to keep her Daughters in a constant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servance of the duty they ought her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander,</hi> having forborn all appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, during all the time that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria</hi> was in Mourning for the Death of her Mother, entreated her now to make good her word, and meeting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with affected delays, he sollicited the Friends and Relations of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> to bring things to a conclusion. <hi>Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35603:33"/> being press'd of all sides, took the opportunity of a discourse, which had divided the Company, to oppose the opinion of <hi>Tazander,</hi> and though he maintain'd it with as much civility, as he ought to have done, yet she seem'd to be offended at his Answers, was as Satyrical upon him, as possibly she could, and designing a Rupture with him, she made as if she took his excuses for a new injury. She after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards gave it out every where, that she had reason to complain of his want of Complaisance, and his incivility, and sent him a Message, to desire him to forbear seeing her any more. On the other side, <hi>Tazander</hi> omitted not any thing, which might conduce either to the appeasing of her, or making their common Friends sensible of the injustice of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s procedure. He was particularly advis'd by <hi>Emerida,</hi> to forbear exasperating a mind, which was to be gain'd by patience. That remedy he thought so tedious, that it was insupportable to him, and a while after, he thought it quite fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, when <hi>Eliciana</hi> would admit of no discourse with him, or receive any of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35603:34"/> his Letters excusing, her self, upon the Prohibition which her Mother had impos'd upon her to do so.</p>
            <p>Though that Beautiful Maiden, did without any repugnance obey upon that occasion, yet had she not the same de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Will of her Mother, when she spoke of bestowing her upon another; nay, she earnestly intreated her, to pardon her, if she could not so soon change the Sentiments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with she her self had inspir'd her. <hi>Asteria</hi> found that excuse too just for her to speak to her any more of it; and <hi>Eliciana,</hi> not finding her self any longer press'd by her Mother, flatter'd her self, that in some time <hi>Oxaris</hi> would return, and might vindicate himself to her. With that Reflection would she say to her self, <q>I have given sufficient Testimonies of my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; I may be allow'd hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to follow my Inclination, since <hi>Asteria</hi> will not any longer force it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>She was thus flattering her self, when she saw <hi>Tazander</hi> coming into the Room, at which sight, being discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd and troubled, she thus scornfully entertain'd him; <q>What, has <hi>Asteria</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:35603:34"/> permitted you to visit me? No, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> I come to acquaint you with the insufferable condition wherewith her Aversion and your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference have reduc'd me. I have been troubled at it, <hi>said she to him,</hi> but you are too Rational a Person to desire, that I should oppose her Will, or that I should not submit to her Commands without ever examining the Justice thereof.</q>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this Discourse a much greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference than he had expected, was so disturb'd, that he continu'd a good while e're he could make any answer. And <hi>Eliciana,</hi> who though she had said enough to disabuse him, was also silent, when upon <hi>Asteria</hi>'s coming in to them, that unfortunate Lover, not giving her the time to express the Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on she might conceive at his being with her Daughter, cast himself at her Feet, and with an intermixture of sighs, address'd himself to her in this Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course: <q>Do you come to my Relief, Madam, <hi>said he to her,</hi> or do you come to give me the last shove into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair? If my Misfortune has been such, as that I have displeas'd you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35603:35"/> my Will, punish me, Madam, by any other way than that of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving me of the Glory of being <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana</hi>'s: And do you, adorable <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana, said he, turning to her,</hi> do you, who know the Grandeur and Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my Passion, appease the Heart of <hi>Asteria;</hi> one word of yours can make her comprehend she owes that which she has rais'd in me, and will prevent my taking of fatal Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if I lose the hope of being yours.</q>
            </p>
            <p>While <hi>Tazander</hi> was speaking this, <hi>Asteria</hi> felt her Indignation increasing against him, by the marks he gave of his Love to <hi>Eliciana;</hi> so that not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him any longer, otherwise than as a person who had slighted her, and of whom she would be reveng'd, <q>Go your ways, <hi>Tazander, said she to him, with a scornful look,</hi> go your ways to find out her who has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proffer'd to you; I am too much your Friend, not to divest you of the pretences which detain'd you in places where you will not find either so much Beauty or so much Wealth as in <hi>Eurimonda.</hi> And for your part, Daughter, <hi>continued she, addressing her
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35603:35"/> self to</hi> Eliciana, think henceforth of bestowing your self on a Man, who may not some time or other reproach you with your being the loss of a greater Fortune to him.</q> After these harsh words she went into her Closet, having given <hi>Eliciana</hi> a sign to follow her, which she did, leaving <hi>Tazander</hi> to encounter with what might be most cruel in so troublesome an Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Is it come to this, said <hi>Tazander,</hi> and are these the Advantages I am to make of the marks of that Affection which <hi>Asteria</hi> and <hi>Eliciana</hi> pretended to me? What implacable rage do I find in the one, and what sickleness in the other! They both express'd an Inclination to make me a happy Man, and they both combine to hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me into Despair. Ah <hi>Tazandar! continued he, after a little respite,</hi> let us satisfy them both, let us go far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from them, since they have so much horrour to see me, and let us go and seek in the hazards of War, the period of both our Life and our Misfortune.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:35603:36"/>
            <p>This Resolution was so fixt in his Mind, that he immediately prepared for the execution of it; but e're he could depart, the desire he had to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit <hi>Asteria</hi> and <hi>Eliciana</hi> once more, was so violent, that he could not oppose it. The next day he went to their House, and having found them alone, without expecting to know whether <hi>Asteria</hi> was pleas'd with his Visit or not, but o'r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd with a new grief, he said to her, <hi>I do not come now, Madam, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you to perform your Promise; an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate person as I am, is far enough from entertaining such sweet hopes; but I come to take my last leave of you, and to assure you, that I am going to court my own Death, without remitting ought of the profound respect which I have ever had for you, and without any diminution of the viloent Love I still continue to</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana. As soon as he had acquitted himself of this Complement, he went out of the Room, without expecting an answer, which he thought would not be much different from those he had already receiv'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliciana,</hi> who had no reason to hate him, could pity his Affliction, yet
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35603:36"/> without any more favourable sentiments for him than she had before: But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria,</hi> who still lov'd him, and could not forbear doing it; coming to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that he was going to expose him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to so many dangers, wherein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate persons, such as he was, are commonly destroy'd; and being not able to recal him, in order to her see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a happy Man with her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was expos'd to all the Rigour which such opposite apprehensions could exercise on a Soul, and went into her Closet, to conceal her disturbance from <hi>Eliciana.</hi> After she had continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there some time, sighing and shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Tears, without knowing precise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what caus'd them, whether Love or Compassion; she consider'd, that Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude was not likely to divert grief, and so out of a desire to dispel it, she went to <hi>Emerida's</hi> where she found Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>As soon as she was come in, they gave over speaking of the sudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of <hi>Tazander,</hi> which they knew was occasion'd by her not permitting him to have <hi>Eliciana. Asteria,</hi> to have it thought that she had heard nothing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35603:37"/> of it, ask'd <hi>Emeridia,</hi> whether she would go into the Country; to which <hi>Emerida</hi> having agreed, they began to talk of the return of the fair season of the Year, and other indifferent things. In the mean time, a Servant of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s enter'd hastily into the Room, all in a fright, and out of breath, insomuch that he could only say these words, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciana,</hi> Madam, <hi>Eliciana! Ah wretch that I am,</hi> cryes out <hi>Asteria,</hi> Tazander <hi>has carried away</hi> Eliciana, <hi>follow after the Villanous Author of the Rape.</hi> The grief which that Reflection caus'd her, was so great, and wrought so suddenly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, that she fell into a Swoun.</p>
            <p>The Men, who at that time chanc'd to be at <hi>Emerida</hi>'s went out for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> without expecting till the Servant had express'd his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and though he affirm'd, that was not the occasion of his coming thither, yet <hi>Emerida</hi> and the other Ladies were so troubled, that they only minded the helping of <hi>Asteria.</hi> But as soon as she had recovered her self, they gave au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to that Servant, and understood that <hi>Eliciana</hi> had not been carry'd away, but that she was dying, being fallen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35603:37"/> ill on a sudden. Whereupon <hi>Asteria, Emerida,</hi> and their other Friends, immediately took Coach, to go and see what condition <hi>Eliciana</hi> was in. As soon as <hi>Asteria</hi> had ask'd her, what she ail'd; <hi>Ah, Madam,</hi> said she to her, with a mournful tone, <hi>how dear has my Obedience cost me!</hi> She had hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly utter'd those few words e're she fell into a second fit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria</hi> beheld her no longer with Eyes of her Passion, but the Affection she had for a Daughter, who was so worthy of it, and the fear she was in of procuring her Death by crossing her Desires, oblig'd her indifferently to intreat those who were in the Room, to run after <hi>Tazander,</hi> and to tell him from her, that he should return, and question not but to find her dispos'd to make him a happy man.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Report that <hi>Eliciana</hi> was dying, coming to <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> just as he was ready to take Horse, made him immediately change his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, flattering himself, that all the grief which <hi>Eliciana</hi> endur'd, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the affliction she conceiv'd at his departure. Thus perswaded, he
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35603:38"/> was going to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, when he met two of his Friends, whom he unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, as to the belief they were of, that he had carry'd away <hi>Eliciana;</hi> and a while after he met with others, who rais'd in him an extraordinary joy, when they told him what <hi>Asteria</hi> had said to his advantage: But that joy was soon alleviated, when he found <hi>Eliciana</hi> in such a condition, as that there was but little hopes of her Life; and when <hi>Asteria</hi> having called him to her Bed-side, <hi>Eliciana</hi> said, turning her self to the other side, without so much as looking on him, <hi>I am now past all Relief, and therefore none is to imagine that he can give me any. Asteria</hi> and <hi>Tazander</hi> not being able to get her to speak any more, withdrew, while <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merida,</hi> who had a tender Affection for <hi>Eliciana,</hi> stay'd with her, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to comfort her, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade her, that her Mother would no longer oppose her desires. <hi>My grief admits of no remedy,</hi> reply'd <hi>Eliciana,</hi> looking very disconsolately on <hi>Emeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> when she found her self alone with her, and so held her peace; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken her by the Hand, which she
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35603:38"/> grasp'd very hard, she gave a deep sigh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> who till then had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly astonished to think, that though <hi>Eliceana</hi> had not given any mark of a violent Passion for <hi>Tazander,</hi> she was yet reduc'd to that sad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon the meer fear of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, did now conclude, that there might be some greater occasion of that extraordinary affliction, and was in hopes that it would be no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to induce her to discover it; but imagining that she was not in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to speak, she thought fit to let her rest till the next day, for fear of aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting her Indisposition.</p>
            <p>The next morning betimes she came to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, and having understood that <hi>Eliciana</hi> had pass'd the night in great disturbances, without receiving any great Consolation from all her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could say to her, and that she had desired, about an hour before, that they would suffer her to take her rest, she apprehended that her desire of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone, proceeded from that of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning her self more freely to her grief, rather than from any thoughts of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:35603:39"/> Repose; and judging that a favourable interval to make her acknowledge what she was desirous to know, she came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Room without any noise; and casting her Eye towards the Bed, found her reading something in a Table-Book, and shedding Tears in abundance.</p>
            <p>As soon as <hi>Eliciana</hi> had perceiv'd <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merida,</hi> whom at first sight she knew not, she was so troubled at her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing surpriz'd in that manner, that desirous to hide the Table-Book, she let it fall. <hi>Emerida</hi> having taken it up, <hi>Eliciana</hi> reaching forth her hand, said to her, <hi>Ah, Madam, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, return it to me before you open it. I would do so, my dear</hi> Eliciana, said <hi>Emerida,</hi> embracing her, <hi>if I were not in hopes to find here what it is that causes your Affliction. And since I have no other desire, than that of being ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to you, be no longer obstinate in concealing from me that which haply will not afflict you any more, when you shall once have acknowledg'd it. Your Mother loves you too well to deny any thing that may promote your satisfaction; and if she had known how much you are concern'd in the happiness of</hi> Tazander, <hi>she not would have demean'd her self as she has done.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35603:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> observing that <hi>Eliciana</hi> was somewhat gravell'd at these words, imagin'd there was some great Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the perplexity she seem'd to be in; and thereupon thus continu'd her Discourse to her, <hi>I shall not restore you the Table-Book, till you have acquainted me with the cause of your Affliction, that so I may the better serve you, giving you this assurance, that I will keep the secret you shall commit to my trust, as long as you shall think it necessary.</hi> That afflicted Beauty having ruminated a while upon what had been said to her, and eas'd her self by several deep sighs; <hi>Do not imagine, Madam,</hi> said she, <hi>that your having got that Table-Book into your hands, and consequently your inferring thence, that you have made a discovery of my secret, is the motive of my acknowledgment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but what I do upon that score, is to assure you of the entire confidence I repose in your Friendship, as also to the end, that if I dye, you may affirm, that I have just cause to be afflicted. But you would be the occasion of an extream trouble to me, if before my death, you acquainted</hi> Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, <hi>or any other person, with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:35603:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> having promis'd her all that she desired, <hi>Eliciana</hi> began to acquaint her with the Passion which <hi>Oxaris</hi> had had for her, and all we have already rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the day of his departure for the Army. <hi>That Table-Book,</hi> continued <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> changing colour, and sighing more deeply than she had done before, <hi>will give you better information than I can, of what has reduc'd me to the condition I now am in. One of his own Servants brought it me but yesterday, while my Mother was at your House. If he has been so meanly Spirited,</hi> said <hi>Emerida,</hi> before she had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Table-Book, <hi>as to fall in love with another, his Inconstancy ought rather to afford you matter of contempt than of grief. Do but see,</hi> said <hi>Eliciana, with a weak voice, how things stand; for 'twould be Death to me, to give you an account of it my self. Emerida</hi> did as she desired, and found these words writ with <hi>Oxaris</hi>'s own hand.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>To <hi>ELICIANA.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce this Letter, Madam, is not to be delivered to you, till after my Death, you will be pleas'd to give me leave to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:35603:40"/> my self, with the hope of your being sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd, that the regret of having offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, has made me seek my punishment amidst the Arms of our Enemies. My Wounds are so great, that giving me only the hopes of a few minutes of life, I am forc'd to write to you in this Table-Book, in the very Field where our Party has been victorious. The person whom I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trusted with it, will give you an account of my last words; in the mean time, I can assure you, that your Indignation has not made any diminution of my Love, and that I shall not speak or think of any thing but you, to the last groan of my Life.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>OXARIS <hi>dying.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>How,</hi> cry'd out <hi>Emerida, is</hi> Oxaris <hi>dead? has</hi> Oxaris <hi>been killed? and is it</hi> Oxaris <hi>who has had so accomplish'd an affection for you? Ah!</hi> Eliciana, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued she, <hi>how just is your grief, and how little reason should I have to condemn the first transports of it! But my dearest</hi> Eliciana, said she to her, embracing her, and intermixing her Tears with the others, <hi>it is now that you are to sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon up all the constancy of your Soul, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:35603:41"/> you may avoid incurring blame, by a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less despair.</hi> She would have proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and press'd all the Reasons she thought capable of Moderating so great an Affliction, had she not perceiv'd, that <hi>Eliciana</hi> was ready to Swound in her Arms. Whereupon having cry'd out, <hi>Asteria</hi> and her People came in to give <hi>Eliciana</hi> the Assistance they were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to give her from time to time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> having not said any thing to <hi>Asteria</hi> of all she had discover'd concerning <hi>Eliciana,</hi> sent out to look for the man whom <hi>Oxaris</hi> had sent. But he, according to the Instructions he had receiv'd from his Master, had only made his appearance to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and was gone immediately out of the City: Mean time, the Letters which came from the Camp, brought Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that <hi>Oxaris</hi> having done pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious things in an Engagement, wherein the Enemy had been Defeated, had been carried, among the other wounded Persons, into a House near the place where they had fought; and that the Enemies having set it on fire, all those who were within had been destroy'd, e're they could be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35603:41"/> reliev'd. All did extreamly bewail the loss of <hi>Oxaris,</hi> as being a young Lord, of very great hopes, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally belov'd.</p>
            <p>Though this was not any thing of News to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> yet was her Grief augmented, not only upon the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of those ill Tidings, but also by the sight of <hi>Tazander,</hi> who was oftner near her than she could have wish'd. But what the Attendances of <hi>Asteria,</hi> and the consolatory applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Emerida,</hi> would never have done, her vigorous Youth, and the strength of her Disposition began to do; and that so effectually, though against her will, that in few days she grew better, and there was no cause of fear, as to her life.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Tazander,</hi> rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the late Promises of <hi>Asteria,</hi> and the assurances which he thought <hi>Eliciana</hi> had given him of her Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, impatiently expected the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of her Health. About that time, there came an Express to him from one of his Unckles, a Man of a great Age, who order'd him to come with all the Expedition possible, to take
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35603:42"/> Possession of a considerable Charge at Court, the Reversion whereof the King had bestow'd upon him. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi> communicated this good News to <hi>Asteria,</hi> and press'd her to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summate his Marriage with <hi>Eliciana,</hi> before his departure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria,</hi> who after she had seen her Daughter out of danger, had reas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum'd her former Passion, found in her self withal, an invincible repugnance to see him Happy with <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and endeavour'd to make him apprehensive of the impossibility there was of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Nuptials, during the Indisposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Daughter. 'Twas to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpose for <hi>Tazander</hi> to remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, that that was not without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and that upon those occasions, the Ceremonies are adjourn'd to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time. He vainly employ'd all hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friends to Solicit her, and to tell her, that he was resolv'd to lose his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion's Employment at Court, rather than quit <hi>Eliciana</hi> before she were secur'd to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria,</hi> having in a manner no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Evasion, bethought her self of giving <hi>Tazander</hi> such assurance as he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35603:42"/> should desire, provided it were not a downright Marriage with <hi>Eliciana;</hi> pretending to be of a Persuasion, that there was something fatal and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astrous in those sorts of Nuptials. In fine, her obstinacy prevail'd so far with <hi>Tazander,</hi> as to content himself with a Promise, that as soon as <hi>Elici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> was recover'd, she would bestow her upon him without any farther delay. <hi>Tazander</hi> had this Promise drawn up, and having dictated it to <hi>Asteria,</hi> she Transcrib'd it, Sign'd it, and Seal'd it with her own Seal, and those of two of the Relations of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> and as many of those of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander,</hi> and then deliver'd it into the hands of that Lover; who thus se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd of his Happiness, went away the next day to find out his Uncle, wthout saying any thing to <hi>Elici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> concerning that Promise when he took his leave of her; for she was yet so weak, as that it was thought convenient, she should be ignorant of what pass'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> who alone knew the cause of <hi>Eliciana</hi>'s Affliction, and tenderly lov'd her, made it her only Business
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35603:43"/> to comfort her, or at least to divert her from her Pensive Reflections, and kept her Company as much as ever she could.</p>
            <p>One Evening, as she was returning to her own House, she was extreamly surpriz'd, to find <hi>Euramantes</hi> present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her with his hand, to help her out of the Coach. <hi>How,</hi> said she to him, after the first Civilities, and as he was conducting her to her Chamber; <hi>is it possible that you should at last remember this Country, after you have been so long out of it? And can your Friends receive you otherwise, than as a Man who has all this while neglected them? But above all,</hi> continu'd she smiling; <hi>how dare you, if I may so express my self, approach the Beauties here, after the Injury you have done them, in having engag'd your self elsewhere, and been insensible to all their Attractions?</hi> At these Reproaches, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimantes</hi> could not forbear Sighing yet made her this Reply; <hi>The Reasons, Madam, which forc'd me to leave these parts, which I never fansied above all the places in the world, are so Cruel for me, that if you had been acquainted with them, instead of accusing me, you would
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35603:43"/> have bemoan'd me; and as the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you reproach me withall, it's possible it would have been more advantageous to me, than that which I had before my absence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> who knew more of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures than he imagin'd, Reply'd; <hi>Come, come, Men do not commonly for so long a time, quit those places, where they have an Engagement. But, Madam,</hi> replies <hi>Eurimantes, when a Man is Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd thence, what can he do more, than return, as I do; and to endeavour by new efforts, to appease her who is the Mistress of my destiny. You speak after such a manner,</hi> says <hi>Emerida, that, if I had not seen certain things, you would make me believe, that you have no Love-obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion elsewhere, What have you seen?</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> somewhat startled at what she had said, <hi>A very Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Picture, and two Love-Letters, which are great Arguments, that a forreign Beauty has a great esteem for you, that you have an extream Passion for her, and that possibly you are already happy. Ah! Madam,</hi> cry'd out <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with indignation against <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, He then, whom I thought the best of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35603:44"/> my Friends has been a second time perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to me: Let him know, that I will not pardon him this second Crime, as I did the former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> being troubled at that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment of his, said to him, with a more serious look, <hi>When you shall be inform'd how</hi> Asteria <hi>and I came to see those Letters, and that Picture, you will have no cause to complain of</hi> Tazander. She thereupon related to him, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver might conduce to the vindication of that Friend, as we have mention'd before; and though <hi>Eurimantes</hi> seem'd to be no farther incens'd against him, yet he made so great a discovery of disquiet, that <hi>Emerida</hi> was of opinion he had fixt his Love elsewhere. Which occasion'd her speaking to him thus: <hi>Though you have heretofore had a Passion for</hi> Asteria, <hi>yet if the change you have made be more to your advantage, it ought not to give you any trouble: For inconstancy being at this day such a defect as most Men brag of, you have no Reason to be Asham'd of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Raillery, Madam,</hi> reply'd <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimantes, does not suit with the posture my Soul is in at present; and if the sight
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35603:44"/> of the Picture and the Letters, which</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander <hi>took from me, gives you any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mind, you shall find, that I can justifie my self; and to that end, I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with what he knew nothing of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Within the two last years of my Voyages, having contracted Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with a young Gentleman of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, named <hi>Elicidor,</hi> of the next Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to this, we Travell'd together into <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> and returning for <hi>France</hi> in a Merchant-Man, we were Attack'd by a <hi>Turkish</hi> Pirate. <hi>Elicidor,</hi> some other Passengers, and my self, perswaded the Master of the Ship, to change the Resolution he had taken to yield, out of a fear of being worse Treated, if he made any defence; and after an Engagement of about three hours, the Valour of our Men, but particularly that of <hi>Elicidor,</hi> forc'd the Pirate to leave us. The joy of that happy Success I soon found aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by a most sensible grief at the wounding of <hi>Elicidor;</hi> when, after the first Dressing, the Wound was thought to be Mortal. When he found Death gaining ground upon him, he thought
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35603:45"/> fit to requite the Affliction which I express'd at his Misfortune; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon have desir'd to speak to me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any others standing by. He thus, with a faint Embrace, address'd himself to me.</q>
               <hi>I have hitherto thought, my dear</hi> Eurimantes, <hi>that my Duty and my Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion enjoyn'd me to, forbear commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating the state of my Soul to you, and to keep it a Secret to my self: But now, that my time in this world is but short, and that I am so Happy, as that I can commit it to the Trust of so Real and so Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Friend, I am to tell you, that, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Lov'd</hi> Eunimonda, <hi>of whom I have often spoken to you, without making any discovery of what I felt for her, that Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Person would have compleated my Happiness, if her Father's Second Wife had not oppos'd it, out of a design to bestow her upon one of her own Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eunimonda, <hi>Scornfully rejecting that Proposition, and peremptorily declaring, that she would be only mine, so incens'd her Father, that by the Advice of my Friends, and by the Command of</hi> Eunimonda <hi>her self, I was oblig'd to go into some remote parts, to try, whether my absence would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce things to their former Station. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35603:45"/> my Travels, I often receiv'd Letters from that Fair one; and it is not above a Month since, that upon the receipt of one, together with her Picture, by an express Messenger, I press'd our repassing into</hi> France, <hi>being inform'd by the said Letter, that her Step-Mother was Dead, and that her Father had consented to my Return. In the mean time, Heaven, as you see, is pleas'd to oppose my Happiness, and leaves me only the Comfort of putting into your hands, the Picture and Letters of</hi> Euni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monda. <hi>The greatest Obligation you can lay upon me, and the greatest Demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you can make of your Friendship towards me, and Remembrance of me, is, that you will restore them to her your self, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to comfort her for my loss.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With those words, he Embrac'd me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, shed Tears abundantly, which made me do the like, and had only the sad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of being assur'd, that I would acquit my self of the Charge he had lay'd upon me, as soon as I could. He Liv'd some hours after, and to the last gasp of Life, his Discourse was wholly about</hi> Euni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monda.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I was as much concern'd and troubled at his Death, as if he had been my own Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35603:46"/> I would not suffer his Body to be cast over-board into the Sea, as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly done upon such occasions; but got it Embalm'd as well as it could be done, and when we were come a-shore, I had it In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd, with all the Ceremonies due to his Merit and Extraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What you intimated to me, continued</hi> Eurimantes, <hi>makes me imagine, that you know how</hi> Tazander <hi>took away the Picture and the two Letters from me, and how he sent them me back again; which having receiv'd, I would not vouchsafe him any answer, as being much incens'd against him for that Action. As soon as I had receiv'd them, I made all the haste I could, to perform what I had promis'd my Friend; and, not to give you any account of what affliction</hi> Eunimonda <hi>endur'd upon the news she receiv'd of the Death of</hi> Elicidor, <hi>nor yet of the pains I took to comfort her, I am to intreat you, to credit what I have said. Nay, to inform your self of the truth thereof: You may the more easily do it, knowing, as you do, the House and Country of</hi> Eunimonda.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> who, by the precedent dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, comprehended, that <hi>Eunimonda</hi> was the very same Lady, of whom
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35603:46"/>
               <hi>Tazander</hi>'s Friends had spoken to her, thought not fit to acquaint <hi>Eurimantes</hi> with it. But to examine,, whether he still had any affection for <hi>Asteria,</hi> she thus continu'd the discourse to him. <q>I need no other Testimony, as to that point, <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> than your own. Let me find you equally sincere in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging who that Person is whom you have lov'd, and whom you do Love at the present, that I may owe that double confidence which you repose in me, to the Ancient Friendship there has been between us. You do not desire any thing of me, Madam, <hi>reply'd</hi> Eurimantes, <hi>sighing,</hi> which it is not my design to acquaint you withal. I do Love, and I have lov'd <hi>Asteria,</hi> from her infancy; I have been Banish'd from her as soon as I could no longer forbear discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Passion, I had for her. From that time, she would never pardon me, not permit me to come near her. But, notwithstanding all her severe Treatments, and my own long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, I have not felt any diminution of that strong Passion; and so I come, though not without some apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35603:47"/> of the impossibility of obtaining my desires, to make a final effort, for the gaining of <hi>Asteria.</hi> Give me therefore, Madam, the advice, or rather, assistance, I beg of you, and I shall owe you all my Tranquillity, and all my happiness.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> pretended to be much sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at a thing, which she already knew; and to avoid discovering to <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> that <hi>Asteria</hi> had spoken to her of him, she oblig'd him to relate to her, the initials and Consequences of his Love; and finding, that her Friend <hi>Asteria</hi> had made her a full and faithful recital of it, she found it so difficult a matter to demean her self with such indifference, as not to do any thing against either of them, that she thought it requisite, to tell <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes,</hi> that he should continue <hi>Incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito,</hi> till such time as she had set him right with <hi>Asteria.</hi> She made him so well comprehend the Reasons which he had, so to comport himself, that, at last, he consented thereto; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the next Morning, at the break of day, he took a Journey into the Country, to a Friend of his, to whom
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35603:47"/> he gave no account of his Love, but made him believe, that he had some Affairs of very great importance, which hindered his appearing publickly, till they were terminated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> having a design to serve <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> and being in hopes, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Asteria</hi> to reassume her former Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, would often take accasion to speak of him to her. And though <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria</hi> still interrupted her, yet it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd one day, that she found her in a disposition to give her Audience. But as she was going to say something of the Letters and Picture which <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi> had taken away from <hi>Eurimantes,</hi> and intended afterwards to proceed to the vindication of that Lover, the Arrival of some Ladies, who came to visit <hi>Eliciana,</hi> prevented her, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd them to go into that young Lady's Chamber, who was already got out of her Bed.</p>
            <p>They had not been long in Discourse, e're another Lady came hastily into the Room, having a Letter in her hand, which she affirm'd that she had receiv'd from her Brother, who was in the Army, and said, <hi>Ladies, I bring you
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35603:48"/> good News,</hi> Oxaris, <hi>whom you have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over for dead, is only a Prisoner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Enemies.</hi> Having so said, she shew'd them the Letter, which gave an account of <hi>Oxaris,</hi> which at first rais'd a great joy amongst them. But there being in it no other particulars, they did not give it that Credit, which the other Lady did.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Elciana,</hi> seiz'd by different apprehensions of fear and hope, was so troubled, that, after she had chang'd her Colour several times, she felt her self growing weaker and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: And the fear of making a disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of her being concern'd in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiny of <hi>Oxaris,</hi> oblig'd her to go into her Closet, whither <hi>Emerida,</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, follow'd her. Whereupon <hi>Asteria,</hi> not finding her in the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and fearing she was fallen ill, went to see how she did. Hearing her sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from an adjoyning Closet, she stay'd a little, and then heard these words. <hi>No</hi> Emerida, said she, <hi>I am not so happy, as that</hi> Oxaris <hi>should be yet alive; It would have been more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to me, if I had not had at first so weak a ground to flatter my self, that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35603:48"/> I should gain a Happiness, which I have lost, by my implicite obedience to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of my Mother. Asteria,</hi> as much surpriz'd, as she was satisfy'd, to find, that <hi>Eliciana</hi> had no Love for <hi>Tazander,</hi> and incited by her own interest, and the desire she had, to gratifie a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so submissive, went into the Closet where she was, and embracing her, said, <hi>Assure your self,</hi> Eliciana, <hi>that if</hi> Oxaris <hi>be living, I will consent to your happiness; and if that news prove not true, comfort your self with this assurance which I give you, that you shall never be</hi> Tazander<hi>'s, nor any other Man's, but by your own free choice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These words fully recover'd <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana</hi> out of the fear which the sight of <hi>Asteria</hi> had put her into; yet could they not flatter her so far, as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade her that <hi>Oxaris</hi> was not dead. There needed greater proofs of that good Fortune, e're she could believe it. Nay, she would not give any Credit to the Letters which confirm'd that news, till after it was known, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies having been inform'd by a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, there was a Person of Quality wounded in the place into which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35603:49"/> they had dispos'd <hi>Oxaris,</hi> some Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, incited by the hope of getting a great ransome for him, had expos'd themselves, to recover him out of the midst of the flames, and had taken care to get his wounds dress'd; and that <hi>Oxaris,</hi> being fully Cur'd, had found some means, to make his escape out of their hands.</p>
            <p>The joy of <hi>Eliciana</hi> was now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Mixture of fear, insomuch that within few days she was in a far better way of Recovery, when a Friend of <hi>Oxaris</hi>'s came, from him, to desire <hi>Asteria</hi>'s permission to wait on her; which request was easily granted. <hi>Oxaris,</hi> who, at his return, had been inform'd, that <hi>Tazander</hi> was not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> went to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, by whom he was entertain'd much more favourably than he could have expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And when she obligingly told him, that, having been extreamly troubled at the news of his Death, he must needs believe, that her joy was no less to find him among the living. <hi>Ah, Madam,</hi> replyed <hi>Oxaris, if you do not give me hopes of a pleasant Continuance of this Life, which I have so strangely reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35603:49"/> I shall endeavour to put a Period to it in greater dangers than I have yet encountred withal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria,</hi> who knew well enongh what oblig'd him to speak at that rate, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd to him, that she was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his Sentiments; nay, made some reproaches to him of his not having made his Applications before <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander;</hi> and promised him, that she would promote his concerns much more than those of his Rival: And to give him some assurances of it, she conducted him to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> who had had so little time to prepare her self for that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview, that she could not forbear discovering too visible a disturbance. She blush'd when he saluted her, and being much more taken with his Person than she had ever been, she found in her self a far greater tenderness for him. <hi>You see, Madam,</hi> says <hi>Oxaris</hi> to her, <hi>that presumptuous person, who has been so unfortunate as to displease you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his will; and though</hi> Asteria <hi>makes but little account of my offence, yet I am ready to undergo a further punishment if you are not pleas'd to pardon it me. You need not any pardon, Sir,</hi> reply'd <hi>Elici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35603:50"/> from me, if it be true that you have obtain'd it of her whose Sentiments shall ever regulate mine. You say much, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> reply'd <hi>Oxaris, when I consider the little I have deserv'd at your hands; but you have not said enough for a Heart which has such a constancy and violence of Affection for you as mine has. Asteria</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that <hi>Eliciana</hi> was somewhat at a loss how to answer him, came oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely to her relief, by changing the Discourse, and obliging <hi>Oxaris</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late what Adventures he had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in, from the time of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>That Lover was so well satisfy'd with <hi>Asteria,</hi> that after he had made all the submissive Acknowledgments he could make of her Favours, and assur'd <hi>Eliciana,</hi> that he was still her most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and most faithful Servant, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to his own House, fill'd with the most pleasing hopes which he had ever had in his Life.</p>
            <p>Having already made his peace with the person whom he had wounded, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him for <hi>Tazander,</hi> and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Inquisition made after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat that had happen'd between them,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35603:50"/> there was nothing hinder'd him from appearing in publick the next day, and receiving the visits of his Friends. As soon as he had dismiss'd them he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, by whom he was receiv'd as a person who did her an honour in having a kindness for <hi>Elicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> and desirous to have their Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age consummated before <hi>Tazander</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, she us'd all the expedition she could for the effecting of it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time most judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were afraid, that <hi>Tazander</hi> would do somewhat which might be fatal to those Nuptials. Nor were they much mistaken, for those whom that Lover had entrusted to write to him, and to give him an account of whatever pass'd in reference to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> having inform'd him, that she was to be married to <hi>Oxaris,</hi> he return'd with all the expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imaginable, and came time enough to intreat <hi>Asteria</hi> to remember what she had promis'd him. <hi>Asteria</hi> gave him some reasons for it, which did not satisfy him; and though he went seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times to her House, yet he still found it impossible for him to speak either with her or <hi>Eliciana.</hi> He knew
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35603:51"/> nothing of the Affection which this young Lady had for <hi>Oxaris,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that procedure seem'd so strange and so new to him, that he examin'd himself, whether he were the same <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi> who had been so much esteem'd by <hi>Asteria,</hi> and so well belov'd by <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana:</hi> He found not any thing in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self which might cause so great a change, and he could not comprehend how, or upon what grounds <hi>Oxaris</hi> should be so highly favour'd, and he so visibly neglected. In fine, not daring to make any complaints against <hi>Elicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> he resolv'd to fight his Rival.</p>
            <p>He sought the opportunity of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him alone; he no sooner found it, but he attack'd him with a fury answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Jealousie. The Combat lasted a good while without any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of either side, till that <hi>Tazander</hi>'s Sword being broken, <hi>Oxaris</hi> cry'd out to him, That he should not force him to kill him. <hi>Tazander</hi> being extreamly exasperated at that misfortune, yet making no answer at all, endeavour'd to close with his Adversary; but <hi>Oxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> being as expert as he was generous, still kept him off, and said to him more
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35603:51"/> than once, <q>Let us be Friends, <hi>Tazander,</hi> force me not to make use of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which Fortune has given me over you, and be perswaded, that it is I who should have cause to complain of your having lov'd <hi>Eliciana,</hi> after she had once approv'd of my Passion.</q>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> smitten at those words, which so many things made likely to be true, and so many others made appear other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, and tyr'd with pressing <hi>Oxaris</hi> to no purpose, with the little he had left him of his Sword, gave over and went his ways, abandoning himself to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, Hatred, Love, and all the most cruel and most contrary Passions; nay, he had some thoughts of hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another Duel with <hi>Oxaris,</hi> but upon better Resolutions, he consider'd, that he could not again attack a Man, who, though his Rival, had been unwilling to kill him, as he might have done. In fine, after several deliberations, he thought his safest and most rational way would be to make use of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise which he had from <hi>Asteria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With that Resolution he went and intreated the Relations of <hi>Eliciana</hi> to tell <hi>Asteria,</hi> that if she bestowed not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35603:52"/> her Daughter on him, he should be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to force her thereto by that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise. <hi>Asteria</hi> was content to execute what she had promis'd him in that Writing, and appointed a certain day, on which, at her House, it should be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd before those of their Relations who had put their Seals to it. As soon as that Lover appear'd before her, he protested to her, in the most civil and most respectful manner imaginable, that he would never have taken that course, had he not been forc'd thereto by a Passion which she her self had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven life to, and approv'd; whereupon, setting his Knee to the ground, he humbly besought her, to grant him, without any Repugnance, that Favour which he begg'd of her, with all the Submissions and Instances imaginable. <hi>Asteria</hi> only made answer, that she was ready to submit to the Laws which she had impos'd on her self; which, as she was saying, she took the Promise out of <hi>Tazander</hi>'s hands, and deliver'd it to one of that Lover's Relations; but instead of finding in it the name of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciana,</hi> they found that of <hi>Asteria. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander</hi> thinking that his Kinsman mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stook,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35603:52"/> caus'd him to read it over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and in fine, he read it himself, and having found that he was not mistaken, his surprise and his grief were so great, that he could not say any thing in a long time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria,</hi> who till then had conceal'd from all the World, the Passion which she had for him, and which it was not in her power to smother, would needs, either out of Pity or Insultation, make a further tryal of <hi>Tazander</hi>'s Patience; upon which Reflection, snatching the Writing out of his Hands, and casting it into the Fire, she thus address'd her self to him; <q>Be not so fond, <hi>Tazan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as to imagine, that it is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to make any advantage of what was contain'd in that Writing: But this you may assure your self of, that as you cannot make any further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> who never had an Affection for you; so on the other side, you are much less to fear that of <hi>Asteria,</hi> who having hitherto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd her weakness from you, will in a short time convince you, that she can triumph over it.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:35603:53"/>
            <p>These words were no sooner out of her Mouth, but that it repented her of having made so plain a discovery of that secret Passion which she had kept so long undiscover'd. The confusion arising thence, together with some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reflections, wrought so violently upon her Mind, that she could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the sight of <hi>Tazander,</hi> and so she withdrew into her Closet, to recover her self out of the disorder she was in.</p>
            <p>Mean time, never was any astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comparable to that of <hi>Tazander,</hi> upon his finding of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s name where he thought to have found that of <hi>Elicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> his being inform'd that <hi>Eliciana</hi> had never lov'd him, and that <hi>Asteria</hi> had had so violent a Passion for him. All these unforeseen things put him to the greatest loss imaginable, insomuch that he in a manner knew not whether he were awake, or in a Dream. In that confusion of thoughts he left <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria</hi>'s, yet not well knowing whither he went; and though they who had been present at that Action were in the Coach with him, and advis'd him not to mind <hi>Eliciana</hi> any longer, yet he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35603:53"/> made them no answer at all; nay, he did not so much as hear them; and he had hardly recover'd himself so far, as to give them thanks when they left him at his own House.</p>
            <p>As soon as he found himself alone, and that his first Astonishment had given his Reason the leisure to examine this strange and magical Adventure, he sometimes thought himself not so unfortunate as he imagin'd before, and at other times he had such an amazing prospect of his destiny, as almost run him into Despair: But at last, for his better information, he went to <hi>Emeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>'s, acquainted her with what had pass'd, and made great complaints that she had not advertis'd him of the Sentiments of <hi>Asteria</hi> and <hi>Eliciana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> compassionating his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, return'd him this Answer; <q>Had I had the knowledge of those Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before, you may be assur'd, <hi>Tazander,</hi> that I should have unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd you; but it is a very short time since I came to know that <hi>Elicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> had no love for any Man but <hi>Oxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> What is that you tell me, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>interrupted</hi> Tazander, <hi>smitten
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35603:54"/> with a new trouble and astonishment?</hi> I am willing to believe, that at the present she has that Sentiment; but after she had made so great discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of her readiness to obey her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on my behalf, and given so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny demonstrations of Affliction when I came to take my leave of her, with a design to put a period to my discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented life, ought I not to think that she had an affection for me at that time, unless I must believe <hi>Eliciana</hi> to be the best skill'd in Dissimulation of any Woman in the World? Ah! <hi>Tazander, said</hi> Emerida, how have you been abus'd by those hopes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Eliciana</hi> ever saw you, <hi>Oxaris</hi> had had the good Fortune to please her; and though her Passion were violent enough, yet the Obedience she ought her Mother, who knew nothing of her Sentiment, made her consent to the choice which she had made of you: Nay, I am further to tell you, that <hi>Eliciana</hi> would not from that time so much as see <hi>Oxaris,</hi> and look'd upon you as the person whom Heaven had design'd to be her Husband. But what is strange and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35603:54"/> remarkable in this Rencounter, is, that she receiv'd the news of the death of <hi>Oxaris</hi> the very same day that you took your leave of her and <hi>Asteria;</hi> and so being overpower'd by her grief, she quite abandon'd her self thereto, as you know; so that you find that you have no cause to complain of her Inconstancy, since she has always persisted in the same Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents for <hi>Oxaris.</hi> And, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd, you ought not to retain any further Animosity against <hi>Asteria;</hi> and what I have told you, I have from <hi>Eliciana</hi> her self.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And as for <hi>Asteria</hi> and her Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards you, I am somewhat astonish'd at it, for I thought her a greater Mistress of her self than I find she has been. It is therefore to be imagin'd, that the Passion she has for you must be very great, since it has occasion'd her doing a thing so contrary to her Humour, and so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to her Reputation. I am no longer surpriz'd at all the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions she found out, to suspend the consummation of your Marriage; for there can be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reason given of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35603:55"/> her acting so preternaturally, as to oppose a thing which she had wish'd to see effected, and of which she her self had first spoken to you, but that she was wholly carried away by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of her passion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> was so far from making the Reflections he ought to have made, on the account which <hi>Emerida</hi> gave him of the sentiments of <hi>Asteria,</hi> that his thoughts were wholly possessed with perplexity and shame, that he had been so long deluded with a perswasion of his being beloved by <hi>Eliciana.</hi> Then did his love begin to degenerate into indignation; but it being impossible that so great a change should be made all of a sudden, he suffer'd himself to be hurry'd away by the first transports of his grief, upon a consideration of the loss he was to make, and would often break forth into this exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <q>O <hi>Eliciana!</hi> why did you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that you had a love for me? O <hi>Asteria!</hi> why did you conceal the Affection you were pleas'd to have for me? Could I have thought you capable of loving me, the very hope of my attempting a correspondence
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35603:55"/> to that love, would have been as prevalent over me, as the perswasion I had was, that I was not displeasing to <hi>Eliciana.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> mov'd with compassion at the weakness of <hi>Asteria,</hi> and the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of <hi>Tazander,</hi> and desirous to render them both more happy, resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to use all the Industry and good Offices she could for the effecting of it. And so, without communicating her design to <hi>Tazander,</hi> she dismissed him, with a promise, that she would inform her self of all the sentiments of <hi>Asteria,</hi> and give him a full account thereof. She thereupon went to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit <hi>Asteria,</hi> who, breaking forth into a blush at her first appearance, said thus to her. <q>What, my dear Friend, do you come to reproach me with my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence, or charge me with a breach of Friendship, in concealing my late weakness from you? I am sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly punished for it, my dear <hi>Emerida,</hi> therefore do not augment my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</q>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> endeavoured what she could to comfort her, and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her that <hi>Tazander</hi> was extreamly troubled at his being ignorant of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35603:56"/> esteem she hath for him. <q>Woe is me! <hi>replies</hi> Asteria, am I so unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as that he should know my weakness? Ah! how am I oppressed with grief, that I have not been able to conceal it from him as long as I lived. Alas! my dear <hi>Emerida,</hi> how afflicting is the very thought of it to me, and what regrets must I expect to undergo?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> stayed with her all that day, using all the endeavours she could, though to little purpose, to alleviate her affliction, and to raise in her some hopes, that things would end more happily than she imagin'd. And so, presuming that <hi>Asteria</hi> would be the next day in a better disposition to submit to her arguments, she return'd to her own house, whither as soon as she was come, some of her Servants brought her word that a certain Person desired to speak with her.</p>
            <p>She at first thought it might be some body from <hi>Tazander,</hi> but she was surpris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to see <hi>Eurimantes</hi> advancing towards her, who seem'd to be in some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary disturbance. She had hardly ask'd him what business brought
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35603:56"/> him thither, and told him she had written to him to this effect, that within few days she would acquaint him with the sentiments of <hi>Asteria,</hi> e'er <hi>Eurimantes</hi> thus interrupted her, <q>I am but too well acquainted, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, with those sentiments, which are so ignominious to her, and which hurry me into despair.</q> He thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gave her an account of what he had been informed of concerning <hi>Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi>'s promise, and the Love she had for <hi>Tazander. Emerida</hi> perceiving that he knew too much, and that it was to little purpose to conceal any thing from him. <q>You have not been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, <hi>said she,</hi> and if I had known it sooner, I should have been adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised by you of it. Alas! <hi>replies</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimantes <hi>sighing, when he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self assur'd of a thing, which he had wish'd not to be true,</hi> how comes it that it is my fortune to love a Person who has an affection for another, who yet has not any for her?</q> He thereupon broke forth into bitter complaints against his own ill fortune, and against the inconsiderate deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Asteria,</hi> which he call'd down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35603:57"/> baseness, and threatned that he would be revenged on <hi>Tazander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida,</hi> to prevent a misfortune which might be fatal to one of those two Lovers, did so well represent to him the little reason he had to hate a man, who was not his Rival, and one who had devoted his love only to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> that she got him to promise her that he would not look after <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander;</hi> but she found it a harder task to obtain this of him, that he would not see <hi>Asteria,</hi> purposely to load her with reproaches. Then having said to him, out of no other design than that of appeasing him, that the belief she had had of his having been in love with <hi>Eurimonda,</hi> had diverted her from vindicating him to <hi>Asteria; Euriman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> continued a while without making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny answer, and at last said to her, <q>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! Madam, there is now no necessity of that Vindication. I have had too great an affection for <hi>Asteria,</hi> and she has done nothing answerably to my Passion. I must therefore forget her, that I may be revenged of her contempt.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:35603:57"/>
            <p>To this he added several other things, which sufficiently discover'd the greatness of his discontent and indignation; and yet there was a dormant sparkle of love for <hi>Asteria,</hi> which made him sigh, when it was least expected from him. <hi>Emerida</hi> desirous to see him quite disengaged from a passion, of which he would never make any advantage, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to him that for his better continuance in the sentiments he was then of, his best course would be to address himself to some other Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who should do his Merit more Justice. <q>Were I to engage my self any where else, <hi>replies</hi> Eurimantes <hi>in a more calm accent,</hi> it should be with <hi>Eurimonda,</hi> rather than any other. She has so favourably hearkned to my reasons, that I have had the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and satisfaction of having in some measure comforted her for the loss she has sustained; and at my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, she so obligingly intreated me not to deprive her long of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation I gave her, that I could a little quarrel with my self, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so constant to <hi>Asteria.</hi> And yet,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35603:58"/>
                  <hi>continued he, not able to forbear sighing,</hi> that ungrateful Lady has still so great an influence over my heart, that I cannot so easily banish her thence, as I could wish; and since it concerns me not to come as much as into her sight, lest I should corroborate a passion, which would be disadvantageous to me, I think it absolutely necessary, that I should remove to some distance from her, and not return till I have clearly forgot her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Emerida</hi> much satisfied to see <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimantes</hi> in that disposition, urged all the arguments, likely to confirm him in a resolution which was yet but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak. But it hapned afterwards, that what was told him of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s violent Passion for <hi>Tazander,</hi> wholly convinced him of the necessity of that Removal. Besides, the remembrance of <hi>Eurimonda</hi> was a powerful attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though he found not himself highly disposed to love her, and that that Passion had been check'd by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of greater strength and stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which now growing weaker, gave way to the latter to bud forth and appear. <hi>Emerida</hi> was extreamly pleased with him at his departure,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35603:58"/> hoping, that being disengag'd from <hi>Asteria,</hi> and well entertain'd by <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monda,</hi> he would admit of a change of Sentiments, and in time, be more happy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander,</hi> in the mean time, was in the most distracted condition imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not knowing what Resolution to fix upon, nor what would prove most advantagious to him. Sometimes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperated by his jealousie, he would vent his indignation by these, or the like complaints. <q>What, shall I suffer <hi>Eliciana</hi> to be at the disposal of <hi>Oxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and not dispute the felicity of that Rival? No, I must either see him ruin'd, or not be a Spectator of his happiness.</q> Then, incens'd against that Beauty, who was the innocent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of his Affliction, he would thus expostulate. <q>To what purpose should I persist in a Love for her, who has so long abus'd me, and made me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit so many Miscarriages?</q> But after all, coming to reflect on the greatness of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s Affection, <q>Unfortunate Man that I am! <hi>said he,</hi> why was I not so happy, as to know, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, what I now only see in a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35603:59"/> Conjuncture, wherein I am uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing any thing correspondent to so high an esteem? Ah, wretched <hi>Tazander,</hi> how sad is thy destiny! Thou art reduc'd to this extremity, that thou lov'st an insensible Person, who slights thy Addresses; and thou canst not submit to those Charms which are more favourable to thee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At last, after several other Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which exasperated him against <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and rais'd in him a tenderness for <hi>Asteria,</hi> he continu'd in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity for the space of two days, not stirring out of his own House, or see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any but his most intimate Friends, who all advis'd him, either to remove to some distance from <hi>Eliciana,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Affection of <hi>Asteria.</hi> He thereupon made a fresh reflection upon all that might induce him to fix upon the latter Resolution. And when ever there occurr'd to his Memory any Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, wherein he was satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd of her Love towards him, he found his thoughts more and more inclining to her; nay so far had he receded from his former Sentiments, that looking on all she had done against him, as so
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35603:59"/> many Marks of a Passion, which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could abate, he came insensibly to Love her; or rather, he discover'd that fire, which the apparent severity of <hi>Asteria</hi> had, till then, in a manner smother'd.</p>
            <p>Being thus persuaded, he began to entertain a great Tranquility of mind, and not doubting but that <hi>Asteria</hi> would give a him favourable reception, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently went to her House. Where, though he found <hi>Emerida</hi> in her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, yet he forbore not casting himself at her feet, and thus address'd to her. <q>I wait on you now, Madam, in a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position much different from that which I had heretofore; I do not only quit all pretensions to the honour of being <hi>Eliciana</hi>'s, but I further make it my humble suit to you, that you would consummate the felicity of <hi>Oxaris</hi> in the enjoyment of her. I had made this request to you, at the very beginning, had I presum'd, to aspire to the Glory of not displeasing you: But, Madam, since my neglect in offering you a Heart, which, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionless, was born only for you, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded wholly from a certain severity
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35603:60"/> I found in you, whereby I was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and discourag'd from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, I could not think it any injury to your Attractions, that I fixt my Love on the most accomplish'd Idea of them. And what I now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press, Madam, is so real, and sincere, that ever since I have assum'd the confidence, of flattering my self, with the thoughts of my not having been indifferent to you, my Love has been, and is still wholly bent upon you, and I cannot disobey you in any thing, unless you should command me not to Love you any longer.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Asteria,</hi> who was incens'd at the long continu'd discoveries of <hi>Tazander</hi>'s indifference, and of an humour too scornful to be wheedled by such Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations, made this Reply. <q>'Tis not the way, <hi>Tazander,</hi> to gain my Love, to tell me that the only motive of your loving <hi>Eliciana</hi> was her resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to me, and her being my Daughter: For what superstructure of any advantage to my self can I make upon your words, if the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations you had for her were the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts of the love and esteem you had
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35603:60"/> for me: You would have prevail'd much more with me, if you had made a sincere acknowledgment of your Love to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and that since your hopes were blasted there, you knew how to accomodate your passion to your interest: Nay, you may add, if you please, that though it was your unavoidable destiny to love <hi>Eliciana;</hi> yet since she is design'd for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of another, and that all in this World cannot obtain their desires, you have a strong fancy that you may prove more successful in the Conquest of another Lady, than you have been in that of her. Whether that fancy may not have somewhat of arrogance and delusion. time will discover, by the success of your Addresses to me, for whom you affirm that your heart was born; and consequently, that I cannot in Civility refuse it. That the Fates have ordain'd will come to pass; but you will find that you have to do with an humour, which as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly capricious, intractable, and not easily cajol'd by the most insinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Complements you can use; so it will be expected, that you should be
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35603:61"/> the less startled at the disappointment of your hopes, when you consider that you have had so fair a pread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertisement of it before hand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> was extreamly surpriz'd at this Answer, because it was at so great a distance from the treatment which he expected; and it may be said, that the very difficulty he fancied to himself, there would be in the Conquest of <hi>Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> so fix'd the Mercury of his Love to her, that he could not think of any other. According to the inspirations of that Sentiment, he gave her all the assurances that could be made by words of the sincerity of his Protestations; but perceiving that he could not at that time prevail with her, and <hi>Asteria</hi> not being willing to give him any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Audience, out of a fear of making him a discovery, what ground those signal demonstrations of a passion which she had so long wish'd, had gain'd upon her heart, he return'd home, encourag'd in his pretensions, by the promises of <hi>Emerida,</hi> to endeavour what she could the removal of those scruples which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria</hi> made against him.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:35603:61"/>
            <p>This prudent Directress of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, who had no other concern than that of being advantagiously and amica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly serviceable to both parties, spoke to <hi>Asteria</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Tazander,</hi> and though she found her not absolutely dispos'd to entertain the vows of that Lover, yet did she conclude her so far inducible thereto, as to tell <hi>Tazander</hi> when he came to examine what progress she had made in the Negotiation, that if he persisted in the Sentiments he had express'd, he had reason to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise himself a happy issue of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses. Upon which encouragement being much heightned in his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he bethought himself that it would be his best course to engage <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aris</hi> to go along with him to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, to make her an absolute discovery of his quitting all pretensions to <hi>Eliciana.</hi> In order thereto, he also entreated the presence of <hi>Emerida,</hi> who was so to manage the interview, as that <hi>Eliciana</hi> her self should hear what he had to say.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxaris,</hi> who had no reason to be an Enemy to <hi>Tazander,</hi> was very ready to serve him; and the next day being
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35603:62"/> come along with him to <hi>Asteria</hi>'s, where, according to her promise, they found <hi>Emerida; Tazander</hi> casts himself at the feet of <hi>Asteria,</hi> and thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress'd to her. <q>I shall never grow weary, Madam, of making you the same Protestations which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made, of the violent passion I have for you; and now I am come to give you the greatest assurance and demonstration you your self can exact of it, since I wait on you, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by <hi>Oxaris,</hi> before whom I now declare, that I transfer to him all the right and pretensions which you were pleas'd I should have to <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and that I protest, in the presence of that adorable Lady, that I have sincerely lov'd her, and that I shall ever love her, not only upon the score of her own merit, but also because she has your very Charms and Attractions. Be therefore overcome, Madam, by the earnest entreaties I make to you, that you would accept of my vows, which if you do, I shall henceforth account my self the happiest Man in the world. And I summon you, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>said he, turning to</hi> Emerida,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35603:62"/> who are so well acquainted with what passes in my heart, to be my witness to <hi>Asteria,</hi> that it is so full of her, that there is no place for any other Object.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this, <hi>Emerida</hi> took occasion to speak afresh on the behalf of <hi>Tazander,</hi> and <hi>Oxaris</hi> having done the like, <hi>Aste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> was convinc'd that she had made a sufficient tryal of that Lover's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy, and had carried her vigorous treatment of him as far as was conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. However, not thinking it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with her reservedness to make him happy all of a sudden, she gave him this answer. <q>I am content, <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zander,</hi> to forget what is past, but I must tell you withall, that I do not conceive my self oblig'd, so inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately to admit of your Vows, since there has been no appearance of them, 'till such time as <hi>Eliciana</hi> had rejected those which you had made to her. If you can afford us your presence at the Solemnities of her Nuptials, without discovering any jealousie or alteration of Sentiments, I promise you that for the future I will examine your passion after a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35603:63"/> more favourable manner than possibly you may think I do at the present.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tazander</hi> was a person of greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension and ingenuity than to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear making his advantage of this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; and having made all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments imaginable of his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions to whatever <hi>Asteria</hi> should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon him; he spoke to her so often, while they were preparing all things for the marriage of <hi>Eliciana,</hi> and <hi>Oxaris,</hi> and so far satisfied her of her having delay'd his happiness long enough, that at last she consented the same day should consummate his feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city with her, and that of <hi>Oxaris</hi> with <hi>Eliciana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Things being thus settled, there was a general exultation amongst those who were any way concern'd therein; and it was the acknowledgment of all, that if they had not been acquainted with those two Beautiful Persons, they would have found but very little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Mother and the Daughter.</p>
            <p>The Solemnities of this double Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage were not quite consummated, e're certain intelligence came, that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimantes</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:35603:63"/> had prevail'd with <hi>Eurimonda,</hi> to put a period to her pensiveness and affliction, for the death of <hi>Elicidor,</hi> and withall to admit him to the same sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in her affections, which the unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected death of that friend had caus'd him to relinquish. And so in process of time, these six Persons, whom so many cross occurrences had threatned with a continuance of their misfortunes, are now arriv'd to such a state of satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and tranquility, as in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance will be of equal extent with their lives.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>